<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The whole duty of a woman: or a guide to the female sex From the age of sixteen to sixty, &amp;c. Being directions, how women of all qualities and conditions, ought to behave themselves in the various circumstances of this life, for their obtaining not only present, but future happiness. I. Directions how to obtain the divine and moral virtues of piety, meekness, modesty, chastity, humility, compassion, temperance and affability, with their advantages, and how to avoyd the opposite vices. II. The duty of virgins, directing them what they ought to do, and what to avoyd, for gaining all the accomplishments required in that state. With the whole art of love, &amp;c. 3. The whole duty of a wife, 4. The whole duty of a widow, &amp;c. Also choice receipts in physick and chirurgery. With the whole art of cookery, preserving, candying, beautifying, &amp;c. Written by a lady.</title>
            <author>Lady, fl. 1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2054B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832397</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36870</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65957)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36870)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2142:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The whole duty of a woman: or a guide to the female sex From the age of sixteen to sixty, &amp;c. Being directions, how women of all qualities and conditions, ought to behave themselves in the various circumstances of this life, for their obtaining not only present, but future happiness. I. Directions how to obtain the divine and moral virtues of piety, meekness, modesty, chastity, humility, compassion, temperance and affability, with their advantages, and how to avoyd the opposite vices. II. The duty of virgins, directing them what they ought to do, and what to avoyd, for gaining all the accomplishments required in that state. With the whole art of love, &amp;c. 3. The whole duty of a wife, 4. The whole duty of a widow, &amp;c. Also choice receipts in physick and chirurgery. With the whole art of cookery, preserving, candying, beautifying, &amp;c. Written by a lady.</title>
                  <author>Lady, fl. 1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 52, 69-104, 113-184 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Gwillim, against the Great James Tavern in Bishopsgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect; stained, frayed and tightly bound, with some loss of print; B6-7 (pp. 11-14), C5-8 (pp. 33-40), D3-10 (pp. 53-68) and F5-8 (pp. 105-112) are lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cookery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:1"/>
            <p>THE Whole Duty OF A WOMAN: Or a Guide to the <hi>Female Sex.</hi> From the Age of <hi>Sixteen</hi> to <hi>Sixty, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being Directions, How Women of all Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Conditions, ought to Behave themſelves in the Various Circumſtances of this Life, for their Obtaining not only Preſent, but Future Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Directions how to Obtain the Divine and moral Virtues of Piety, Meekneſs, Modeſty, Chaſtity, Humility, Compaſſion, Temperance and Affability, with their Advantages, and how to avoyd the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Vices.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Duty of Virgins, Directing them what they ought to do, and what to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd, for gaining all the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments required in that State. With the Whole Art of Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. The Whole Duty of a Wife, 4. The Whole Duty of a Widow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo, Choice Receipts in Phyſick, and Chirurgery With the Whole Art of Cookery, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, Candying, Beautifying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by a Lady.</p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Gwillim,</hi> againſt the <hi>Great James Tavern</hi> in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED according to Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. Poplar</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE, TO Ladys, Gentlewomen, and others, of all Degrees.</head>
            <p>HAving had a Liberal, Education and many Opportunities to Improve what my Younger years were Seaſoned with, I have been no ways Neglectful to my ſelf or others, in Gaining Knowledge and Experience in ſuch vſeful things, as not only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready have, but further will, prove Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to both; and much Oblige Poſterity, when I am Reſting in a Silent Grave, by a Seaſonable Publication of
<pb facs="tcp:36870:3"/>them. For, ſince Age grows fast upon me, it is but Neceſſary I ſhould do all the Good I can, before I go out of this World, that I may find the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it in another.</p>
            <p>Three things we are Chiefly Born for, Viz.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. TO Serve GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Our Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Laſtly <hi>Our Slves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though ſome, not minding this Rule, make the Latter the only Scope of their Lives; but are more Lightly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned about the two Antecedents: Yet their Practices ought to be no Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, nor Example.</p>
            <p>You will find in this Work, ſuch Variety of all things, properly Adapted to our <hi>Sex,</hi> that you muſt <hi>(I believe)</hi> Confeſs, there is nothing that Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Contributes to a perfect Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Management, in the ſeveral Stages, or Stations of Life, Omitted, And therefore I could Frame to my Self no properer Title, than that of
<pb facs="tcp:36870:3"/>
               <hi>The Whole Duty of a Woman.</hi> Eſpecially from the Age of <hi>Sixteen,</hi> to <hi>Sixty:</hi> For between theſe periods there is found <hi>the Trueſt Portion of Good in this Life.</hi> If it be Conſidered, that on the other ſide, firſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is Weak and Green, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncapable of forming Sound Notions, of things Solid, and Subſtantially profitable; either as they tend to Outward, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Tranquility. And paſſing the Latter, Age, and its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſy Attendants, frequently Debilitate the Faculties; and as it were, Seiz on, and Carry away the Memory, in a large Degree; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it may Tollerably in one Senſe or other, ſuit Tender Years, and Extream Age, by Directing them in ſuch Ways and Methods, as cannot but reaſonably Afford them all reaſonable Advantages, and Satisfaction; eſpecially to keep up a Healthful Conſtitution here, and Teach them to Trace thoſe paths of Virtue, that Lead to the Well-Springs of Life, and Endleſs Health hereafter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:4"/>
            <p>But not to Delay your Expectation, in dwelling long on a <hi>Preface,</hi> never doutbting, but it will ſufficiently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it ſelf, without any further <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> I Bequeath it to you as my <hi>Legacy;</hi> and indeed, the laſt in this kind, I ſhall be capable of Preſenting you withal; Hoping you will Seriouſly Weigh and Conſider it, as it was Meant, and Intended for your Good and Singular Advantage.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36870:4"/>
            <head>THE Whole Duty OF A WOMAN.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Directions how to Obtain the Divine and Mortal Vertues of Piety, Meekneſs, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, Chaſtity, Humility; Compaſſion, Temperance, and Affability; with their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages: And how to Avoy'd the oppoſite Vices, as Impiety, Obſtinacy, Immodeſty, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Pride, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperence, and Diſdain; with the Miſchiefs that attend them.</head>
               <p>BEING to Treat of the many Graces and Vertues that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to be ſtrictly Obſerved by our Sex, I think I cannot do better than to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with that which more, immediatly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ired to Beautifie the Soul; and ſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt in order.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36870:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piety</hi> then is an excellent adornment to the Soul and Body. And indeed <hi>Sollomon</hi> well Admoniſhed, when he bid you <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your, Creator in the days of your Youth,</hi> for your Duty to God is an Introduction to all other Felicities in this World, and that to come</p>
               <p>Be therefore mindful of this, <hi>Pray</hi> earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly, that he may enable you in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formence of it. <hi>Meditate</hi> on this Love and Kindneſs towards you, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Bleſſings, and encreaſe them to your comfort. Conſider you are wholy Gods Portion, by title of Creation; and that whatever you enjoy proceeds from him, as the Waters Flow from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: And therfore all your Endeavours Faculties, and Powers muſt be entierly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his Service, in doing all the good you can, our Sex being priviledged with great advantages of this Kind, by reaſon of the leiſure that have to proceed in it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not alone ſufficient that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God is imprinted in our Minds, but it muſt be put into Practice, and nothing that is in your power omited; and if you fail in either, you muſt re-double your, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, to re-call the time you have ſpent a miſs; with full reſolutions and purpoſes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36870:5"/>to be more cautious for the future. And be often in <hi>Meditation</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> That no Temptation may find an opertunity to ſix upon your wandering Thoughts; theſe two are the main Pillers of <hi>Religious Duty.</hi> They are like the <hi>Spies</hi> that ſearched the Land of <hi>Canan,</hi> the one views and the other gathers and brings it home as the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Fruits of Heaven. <hi>Meditation</hi> like the Eye, views our Mercies; and <hi>prayer,</hi> like the Hand, reaches to us thoſe Mercies: Or <hi>Meditation</hi> is like a Factor, who goeth abroad to gather in what you want; and <hi>Prayer,</hi> like a Ship, goeth forth and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to you what you deſire: And is both the Duty of the ſoul and Body.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let God be all in all with you; ſet your affections upon nothing that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide you from him, for that is a Robing him of his Honour; and then Remember he is a Jealous God Love him with all your Heart, and all your Soul, and all your Strength.</p>
               <p>Be in Kindneſs and Charity with all People. Relieve thoſe that are in want according to your Ability. Inſtruct thoſe that do Amiſs; and Perſwade them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and reform their Lives. Give no occaſion of Scandal or Reproach: but let
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36870:6"/>your Converſations ſet an Example to other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your Private Devotions be Frequent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and in the publick Aſſemblies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Worſhip, behave your Selves with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Modeſty, and becoming Decency <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neither your Thoughts nor Eyes warder. Be attentive and fix your mind on what was the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your coming thither, that Gods Grace may flow to you, and ſo his Word may be Imprinted in your Hearts. Forget not to <hi>Communicate;</hi> but above all be ſure by Prayer, Self-examination, Works of Mercy and Charity, to prepare your ſelves for the reception of that Adorable Myſtery. Let not Anger nor Paſſion prevail over you, but be Humble and Meek, and ſo ſhall you proſper in all your ways. You ſhall have a goodly heritage, and your line ſhall fall happily in a fair Land: For the Lord ſhall be your Portion, and your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Reward. He will give you the Bleſſings of the Right Hand and of the Left; Protect and keep you ſafe in this life, and in the next make you to Dwell with him in Eternal Glory. When on the contrary</p>
               <p>Impiety is that which Poiſons the Sweets of Life, Taints you Names and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36870:6"/>Reputations, and Wounds your Souls; Lays perpetual Snares and Stumbling-blocks in your way, to make you fall into various miſchiefs. But that which is moſt grievous to be born, it makes God your Enemy in the end; whoſe Anger is ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than a two Edged Sword. In brief, Sin is a Monſter that came into the World by the diſobedience of our firſt parents; and brought with it a world of woes; and though the Devil, who is its Parent, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, by his Agents, very induſtriouſly, to cover its Deformities, under borrowed names and ſpecious pretences, yet, to the Eyes of the Vertuous, it is ſo Ugly and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that it is to be loothed and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for beſides the innumerable miſchiefs it compaſſes here, to unthinking Souls, as it at its firſt enterance brought our Temporal Death along with it, ſo, if you hug it in your Boſom, and carry it out of the world with you, it will lead you into Eternal Death and Damnation. Therefore as it is an Enemy to God, be you always at enmity with it, ſo that at laſt you may arive at the end, of Glory, by all the ways of Grace, Prudence and Religions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meekneſs</hi> is not only Recommended to all, as a Chriſtian Vertue, but particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36870:7"/>to Women, as a peculiar Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Sex. And St. <hi>Peter,</hi> after the mentioning of all exquiſite and coſtly Deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Art, commends to you above all, this one Ornament <hi>of a Meek and Quiet Spirit;</hi> with this eminent atteſtation, <hi>That it is in the ſight of God of great Price.</hi> And therefore to all that will not enter into Diſpute with God, and Conteſt his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it muſt be ſo. But although <hi>Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> be in it ſelf an entire ſingle Virtue, yet it is Diverſified according to the ſeveral Faculties of the Soul, over which it has Influence; ſo that there is the <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> a <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of the <hi>Will,</hi> and a <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of the <hi>Affections;</hi> all of which concur to make up a <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>quiet Spirit.</hi> And of theſe in their Order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> conſiſts in a pliableneſs to Conviction, owning our Faults and unworthyneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repining.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of the <hi>Will</hi> lies in its ſubordination and ſubmiſſion to a more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority, which is, Divine things, is <hi>The Will of God;</hi> and in Natural and Morral, <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and in Human conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>the Command of Superiours:</hi> And ſo long as the <hi>Will</hi> Governs it ſelf by theſe,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36870:7"/>in their reſpective orders, it tranſgreſſes not the <hi>Meekneſs</hi> required of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of the <hi>Affections</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in reducing the Paſſions to a Calm Temper, not ſuffering them to make up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roars within, to diſturb ones ſelf, nor without, to diſquiet others; and to this Regulation <hi>Meekneſs</hi> is generally Subſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Its Oppoſites are then to be compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Threefold, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Conceitedneſs,</hi> That is a Fancy that all you do is ſtamp'd as Standard, and paſſes Current in your own Conceit, how bad ſoever your Actions appears in the Eyes of others, or are really ſo in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, being your own Judg without hearkning to convincing Reaſons, or juſt Reproof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Obſtinancy</hi> in Reſiſting the motions of Gods Holy Spirit, or hearkning to the wholeſome Advice and Directions of thoſe he has ſet over you, to watch for your Soul. And in the Second Branch, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the Powers he has Ordained, and put in Authority over you, ſpurning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reaſon and Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Inordinate Paſſions</hi> troubleſome, to your ſelves and others as <hi>Revenge, Fury, &amp;c.</hi> But that you may Avoid theſe, hear what
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36870:8"/>our Saviour ſays, <hi>viz. Bleſſed are the</hi> Meek <hi>in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Modeſty</hi> is properly termed, <hi>The Science of Decent Motion;</hi> as being a guider and regulater of all decent and comly Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and Behaviour; Checking and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ouling Rudeneſs, and any thing tending to Confidence and unmannerlineſs; and is held the great Civilizer of Converſation; Ballancing the Mind with humble and ſober thoughts of your Selves, and Ordering every part of the outward frame, in the moſt winning and obliging manner.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It appears in the Face in calm and comly Looks, where it makes due impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; ſo that it ſeems from thence to have Acquired the Name of <hi>Shame-facedneſs.</hi> And truly, what ever the Modern Opinion of ſome may be, there is nothing adds a greater Luſtre to <hi>Feminine Beauty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Modeſty</hi> confines it ſelf not to the Face only, for there it may, in ſome ſenſe, be ſaid to be in Shadow and Effigie, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>preads it ſelf in life, Motion and Words: baniſhing all Indecency and Rudeneſs; all Inſolent Vauntings and Supercilious Dains, or what elſe may render our Sex trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome or uneaſie to Company or Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. It Refines and Tunes the Language,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36870:8"/>Modulates the Tone and Accents; not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Intruſion of unhanſom, earneſt, or Loud Diſcourſe. So that the Modeſt Tongues is like the imaginable Muſick of the <hi>Spheres,</hi> ſweet and charming, but not to be heard at diſtance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As <hi>Modeſty</hi> preſcribes the manner, ſo it alſo does the meaſure of Speaking. It reſtrains all exceſſive Talkativeneſs, for that indeed is one of the greateſt aſſumings imaginable; and ſo rude an impoſing on Company, that there can ſcarce be a greater Indecency in Converſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Modeſty</hi> therefore ought, if you have reſpect to Vertue and a good Name, to appear in it's higheſt elevation. Your Looks, your Speech, and the courſe of your whole Behaviour, ſhould own an humble diſtruſt of your ſelves; rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to learn and obſerve, than to dictate and preſcribe, unleſs upon very Emergent occaſions, and that to thoſe that are rambling in the Paths of looſneſs. And therefore, as you value your Reputation, keep up to the ſtrictneſs of this Vertue, leaſt when you conceive it not amiſs, in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial matters, to launch beyond the bounds of Modeſty, you are violently carry'd too far to Retreat before you are aware; as I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36870:9"/>ſhall ſhew you in the contrary on this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Adornment of our Sex.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Immodeſty</hi> is held, even in <hi>Heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> a great Reproach and Scandal, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where it is found in Women; and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſpoke by an excellent Spirit, Commands, <hi>That Women Adorn themſelves in Modeſt Apparrel, with Shamefacedneſs, and Sobriety; not with Broidered Hair, or Gold, or Pearl, or coſtly Array, but (which becometh Women profeſſing Godlineſs) with Gods Works,</hi> 1. Tim. 2.9. So that when thoſe that are not well affected to Modeſty, have ſtrained their Art to the higheſt pitch, an <hi>Innocent Modeſty</hi> and native Simplicity of Looks, will Eclipſe their Imaginary Splendor and Triumph over their Artificial Beauties. And indeed, if a Woman be Adorned with all the Embelliſhments of Art, and care of Nature to boot, yet, if Boldneſs Scorn, and haughty Looks be imprinted in her Face, <hi>They blot out all the Lines of Comelineſs, and, like a dark Cloud over the Sun, ſhade the view of all that was otherwiſe Amiable; and renders its blackneſs but the more obſervable, by being placed nearer ſomewhat that was apt to attract the Eyes, and leave a ſtrain on their Names and Reputations.</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                     <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36870:9"/>burning deſires and impatient wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Tediouſneſs, Delay, Sufferance of Affronts, and Amaſement of Diſcovery. Chaſtity, above all, is ſo eſſential and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to our Sex, that every declination from it, is a proportionable receding from Whomanhood; but the total abandoning it, ranks you among Bruits, and ſets you as far beneath thoſe, as anquired vileneſs is below a native. An Unchaſt Woman is look'd upon as a kind of a Monſter; a thing devided and diſtorted from its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per form, eſpicially by Chaſt and Vertuous Perſons. And I dare Appeal to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt of them, that thus go aſtray (and in diſhonouring themſelves, give occaſion of Scandal to our Sex) whether, at firſt, they could not with more eaſe have kept their Virtue than have loſt it? Certainly ſuch are the Horrors and Shame that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds thoſe firſt Guilts, that they muſt, as it may be termed, commit a Rape upon themſelves, (force their own reluctancy and averſions) before they can become wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Proſtitutes to others; this their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers ſeem wellenough to underſtand, and upon that ſcore, are at the pains of ſo many preparitive Courtings, and expence of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, as if this was ſo uncouth a Crime,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36870:10"/>that there were no hopes t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>troduce it, but by a Confederacy of ſome more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Vices, as Pride, or Covetouſneſs: Therefore have a care of the Snares.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Know you not,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, That your Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this be ſo, will you defile it, when God himſelf threatens to deſtroy you if you do? But I ſhall conclude this Section Briefly, in the words of St. <hi>Gregory, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is the Parent of theſe Monſters,</hi> viz. <hi>Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mind, Inconſideration, Precipitancy or Giddineſs in Actions, Self Love, Harred of God, Love of preſent Pleaſures, a diſpight or diſpaire of the Joys of Religion here, and of Heaven hereafter. Whereas a Pure Mind, in a Chaſt Body, is the Mother of Wiſdom and Deliberation, Sober Councils, and Ingenious Actions, Open Deportment and Sweet Carriage, Sincere Principles, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprejudiced <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Love of God, and Self Denial, Peace and Confidence, Holy Prayers, and Spiritual Comforts, a Pleaſure of Spirit infinitely greater than the Fooliſh and Beaſtly Pleaſures of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtity.</hi> And therefore to overcome it, is certainly the greateſt Pleaſure; for indeed no Victory is greater than that which is gotten over Luſtful Inclinations.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36870:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humility</hi> is a great Ornament to your Sex; and the Graces of it are Exerciſed by the following Rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Think not your ſelves better for any thing that happens to you from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, for though you may have many Gifts beſtowed upon you better than others, yet conſider you are a Mortal Creature, wholly relying; as well as others, upon Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, Mercy, and Providence; and have nothing to commend you to your ſelf, but that you have a little time to imploy in his Service who brought you into the World, and in whoſe hands are all your Riches, and Honours; and even your <hi>Breath of Life:</hi> Who can, if he pleaſes, take from you what he has given, and beſtow it on the Pooreſt and Meaneſt Perſon on Earth. However, <hi>Humility</hi> conſiſts not in Railing againſt your ſelf, or in going in baſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, walking ſoftly or ſubmiſſively, but in a hearty &amp; mean Opinion of your ſelves; being content to want Praiſe or outward Applauſe, not troubled or angry when you are ſlighted or undervalued. Never be aſhamed of your Birth, or Parents, or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; for the Meanneſs or Poverty of any of them, but ſpeak as readily and indifferently of Meanneſs as you would do of Greatneſs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36870:11"/>
                  <hi>Primiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> was raiſed (by the <hi>Queen</hi> caſting her Affections acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially on him as ſhe paſſed by his Field) from the <hi>Plough</hi> to the <hi>Throne,</hi> yet was ſo humble, That he kept his country Shoes always by him, to put him in mind of his lowly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And King <hi>Agathoeles</hi> Furniture of his Table demonſtrated that he was raiſed from a <hi>Potter</hi> to be <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Sicily.</hi> But why need I inſiſt upon theſe? When the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> propounded himſelf to Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by his Diſciples, ſo Signally in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as in the <hi>Twin Siſters,</hi> viz. <hi>Mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſs</hi> and <hi>Humility, Learn,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of me, for I am Meek and Humble, and you ſhall find Reſt to your Souls</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Never ſpeak any thing directly tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your own Praiſe, that is, on purpoſe to be Commended; and when you have ſaid or done any thing for which you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid receiving Praiſe, take it indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently; and then diſrobing your ſelf of it return it to God; Reflecting upon him as the Giver of the Gift, or the bleſſer of the Action: And give him thanks for making you an Inſtrument of his glory, or the Benefit of others. Secure a good Name to your ſelves, by living Virtuouſly and Humbly, but let it be Nurſt abroad, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36870:11"/>not in your own Boſom. Let your Faces, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhine to others, but make no looking-Glaſs for your ſelves. uſe no Stratagem or devices to get praiſe, nor ſeek for any reward here, but walking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and humbly with God, and thoſe you Converſe with here, you ſhall one day be exalted to Heaven, when the Proud and haughty ſhall ſink in the depth of Miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pride</hi> is Oppoſite to <hi>humility,</hi> as Light is to Darkneſs; and indeed in the laſt day, The latter will lead you to the firſt, and the former, thoſe that court it, to the laſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider then what ſuch vile Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs, who are but Duſt and Aſhes, have to be Proud of: If of our Bodis, thoſe are week and impure, ſubject to Diſeaſes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays, to Die, Corrupt in a Grave, and turn to Rottenneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it your Strength you boaſt or <hi>grow</hi> proud in? In that you are inferiour to many Irrational Creaturs: Nay, That which makes too many of our Sex Proud and look down with diſdain, even the conceit of beauty, is of no value, to make ſuch a ſwelling in their minds, ſeeing, in colour and fragrancy, they are Rivalled and out done by various Flowers; and when it is moſt florid and gay, a few Agus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36870:12"/>Fits change it into paleneſs, and Wrinkles of Deformity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If Proud of Learning or Parts, the firſt of theſe, in its proper ſphere, runs contrary to Pride, teaching Humility, The ſecond, Civility and a modeſt behaviour. To be Proud of Riches is yet more Fooliſh; for if you will exalt your ſelf above others becauſe you have more Gold, conſider, at your own rate, how much you are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to a Gold Mine; how much you are to give place to a Cabinet of Jewels. If Proud of your Birth, you are Proud of the Bleſſings of others, not of your own; For if your Parent were more Eminent in any circumſtance than your Neighbours, you are to thank God, and Rejoyce in them more than any value in your ſelf. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber then to check all pride in your mind; For what were you before you were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? Nothing. What in the firſt Regions of your Dwelling, before your Birth? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs. What for many years after? Weakneſs. What in all your Life? A great Sinner. What in all your Excellencies? A meer Debtor to God, to your Parents, to the Earth, and to many Creatures. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi> but on theſe things, and you will ſoon find there is nothing more reaſonable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36870:12"/>than to be Humble, and nothing more fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh than to be Proud.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Compaſsion</hi> ſeems-Natural to our Sex, whoſe ſoft Breaſts were made to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain tenderneſs and pitty So that I find <hi>Solomon</hi> could not conclude the Character of his <hi>Virtuous Women</hi> without it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.20. <hi>She ſtretcheth forth her hands to the Poor; and rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heth her Bread to the needy.</hi> That is, She was Compaſſionate, and had Bowels full of Mercy; and when ſhe ſaw any poor object, it did, as it were, command an Alms. So that the Application is very obvious, and Admoniſhes all that own the title of <hi>Vertuous VVomen,</hi> to prefer the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of others before their own Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities and Delicacies. Nay if you look further, and conſider who it is that is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonated in the Poor, that Beggs in every needy diſtreſſed ſuppliant, and that will own every act of Mercy as done to himſelf, you will moderate your Enjoyments, and exerciſe yous ſelves in this act of <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> as aſham'd to ſerve your ſelves before the Poor, or let them ſtand Naked, or Hungry, whilſt you are ſollacing whith that which would Relive them; leaſt at the General Day, when you ſtand in the greateſt need, you be juſtly upbraided with this want of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36870:13"/>
                  <hi>Compaſſion;</hi> and Eternally excluded from all Comforts, becauſe you refuſed to lend my ſuccour to his Diſtreſſed Members on Earth, which he takes as done unto himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider if the Bowels of Gods ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercy ſhould be ſhut up towards you, in what a miſerable condition you would be, when from his bounty proceeds all that you Enjoy. Look up to the giver with a ſerious Contemplation of Mind, and you will ſoon perceive to what end his Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are beſtowed upon you; and find the Stock he has Lent, is mainly to Try you in this <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> or <hi>Charity,</hi> to thoſe he has reſtrained the things of this World from; And then you will find it a very commendable Induſtry, to qualify your ſelves to be helpful to the <hi>poor,</hi> in as many Inſtances as you can: In not only opening your <hi>Purſes,</hi> but <hi>Diſpenſatories,</hi> to provide <hi>Medicines</hi> for ſuch as by <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> or <hi>Caſualty</hi> want that ſort of Relief. A <hi>Charity</hi> which I dare not belive but is practiſed by many, and I wiſh it ware by more; That our <hi>Niſer Dames</hi> who Study only <hi>Coſmeticks</hi> for themſelves, would change the Scene, and inſtead of <hi>Reparing,</hi> or rather <hi>Diſguiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> their own <hi>Complections,</hi> Study the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the <hi>Decrepit Limbs</hi> of poor Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliants:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36870:13"/>And certainly, though it be leſs Faſhionable, it is a much better ſight to ſee a <hi>Lady</hi> binding up a Sore, then Beautifying her Face; and ſhe will caſt a much ſweeter favour in Gods Noſtrils, with the Smell of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguents</hi> and <hi>Balſams,</hi> then with the moſt exquiſit <hi>Odours</hi> and <hi>Perfumes.</hi> For ſince God profeſſes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. That the very <hi>Incenſe</hi> deſigned for a part of his Worſhhip, was an Abomination to him, becauſe not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the <hi>Acts of Mercy,</hi> we cannot imagine he will better approve of thoſe, who have no higher aim then <hi>Delicacy</hi> and <hi>Senſuallity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Beſides this part of <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> there is another act of <hi>Mercy;</hi> which is to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give Injuries, laying aſide all reſentments and thoughts of Revenge, though to ſome of the hot Spirits of our Sex, this may be thought a very hard Leſſon, yet if they do not, they muſt confeſs they diſſemble with God, when they ſay <hi>The Lords prayer,</hi> or at leaſt not expect to be <hi>forgiven thoſe Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> which they implore a Pardon for. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider yet again, That God knows the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of all Hearts, and if we forgive not others, we cannot expect to be Forgiven.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Uncharitableneſs</hi> is that which Strikes at the Foundation of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36870:14"/>And thoſe that deveſt themſelves of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> but in vain declare them ſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> For, what can you think of your ſelves, when you willfully diſobey what <hi>Chriſt</hi> has chiefly Enjoyner you, and in Lieu of it, promiſes Salvation And more ſpecially, How can you anſwer it if you ſuffer him to be Supplanted in his poor ſuffering Members, not only be your Needs, but Exceſſes, who have ſo devoted your Hearts to <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Luxury,</hi> That you have neither Will nor Power to ſuccour the wants of others? How unequal and diſproportionate is it, That thoſe that Study fling away Money on themſelves, cannot be tempted, by any oppertunity or diſtreſs, to Drop an <hi>Alms</hi> to the <hi>Poor!</hi> What a Propoſterous ſight, it is, to See a <hi>Lady</hi> whoſe Gay Attire gives her the glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of the Sun, yet has nothing of its other Properties, never to chear any Drooping, Languiſhing Creature by her Influence? It is the Council of the son of <hi>Sirach, Not to give the Poor any occaſion to Curſe you Eccl.</hi> 4.5. but ſure ſuch Perſons do it, if the Poor have not a greater <hi>Charity</hi> than they exemplifie to them; for when they find ſuch <hi>Hard Hearts</hi> under ſuch <hi>Soft Raiments,</hi> and a <hi>Poor, Starving Wretch</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36870:14"/>ſhall look upon ſuch <hi>Gay Creatures,</hi> and ſee that any one of their <hi>Baubles</hi> and <hi>Looſe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendages,</hi> or <hi>Dreſs,</hi> bear a price that would warm their <hi>Empty Bowels,</hi> and refreth their <hi>Fainting Spirits,</hi> 'tis a ſhrewd tryal of their <hi>Meekneſs. Poverty</hi> is apt enough of it ſelf to imbitter the spirit, and needs not ſuch an additional Temptation. Let this, I ſay, be now ſeriouſly Remembred, leaſt you fall hereafter under the ſame exprobrating Remembrance with the Rich Man in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> Luke 16.25. <hi>Remember that thou in thy Life-time receivedſt thy good things, and</hi> Lazarus <hi>that which was Evil; but now he is comforted and thou art Tormented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides this part of <hi>Mercy</hi> in giving <hi>Alms,</hi> there is another, which is <hi>forgiving Injuries</hi> to Perſons of all Ranks: This is that part of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> which we peculiarly call <hi>Clemency;</hi> a <hi>Virtue</hi> which not only <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> but <hi>Morality</hi> recommends. The <hi>Heathens</hi> were admired in this; and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> far exceeded them in the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times,</hi> following the Example of their great <hi>Lord and Maſter,</hi> who prayed for his Crucifiers, <hi>viz. Father forgive them,</hi> &amp;c. Luke 31.34. But now we find it much altered, &amp; therefore it ought to be amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe that expect to be forgiven of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36870:15"/>God, <hi>Revenge</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> being the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of Satan, having innumerable Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and Miſeries attending them; and therefore they muſt be avoided as Monſters made for Ruin and Deſtruction. It ſhould therefore methinks be an eaſie determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether to Embrace that <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi> which you ſee Exemplified in the Wiſeſt and Beſt of Men, or that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Fierceneſs</hi> of the Ignoble Creatures. This is certain, That there is not any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would be contented to aſſume the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form of any <hi>Ravenous, Revengeful Creature.</hi> Why then ſhould you ſubject your Nobler Parts and Mind to ſuch Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation? For as there is no <hi>Monſter</hi> ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed as thoſe Compounded of <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſo nothing can be more Unnatural, or Odious than a <hi>Woman Tyger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Temperance,</hi> as <hi>Sobriety</hi> is the <hi>Bridle</hi> of the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſo <hi>Temperance</hi> is the <hi>Bitt</hi> and <hi>Curb</hi> to reſtrain us to a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate uſe of Meat, Drink and Recreations, ſo that they may beſt conſiſt with our Health, and not hinder, but help the work of the <hi>Soul,</hi> by the neceſſary ſupports they adminiſter; and this principally conſiſts in the <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Soul,</hi> for it is a <hi>Grace</hi> that chuſes <hi>natural means</hi> in order to promote
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36870:15"/>
                  <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Holy Ends.</hi> It is Exerciſed in <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> becauſe they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, however it permits the uſe of them only as they Miniſter to <hi>Lawful Health;</hi> but when <hi>Delight</hi> is the only End, and reſts and dwells there long, tending to <hi>Riot,</hi> there it is the contrary; for ſuch <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking</hi> is not a <hi>Serving God,</hi> but an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Action,</hi> becauſe it is not in the way to that end: And to avoid theſe Latter,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be not often at great Feaſts, nor at all in Diſſolute Company, for variety of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Steals away the Heart; and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is either Violent or Enticing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be ſevere in your Judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Proportion, and ſuffer no occaſion to make you enlarge beyond what is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, leſt you exceed the bounds of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; and as you take this caution your ſelf, never urge any one to <hi>Eat</hi> or <hi>Drink</hi> beyond their deſires. Take, in this, St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Advice, <hi>Let us, who are of the day, be Sober,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Begin and end your time with <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,</hi> ſo that you may carry your Mind and spirit to the <hi>Coeleſtial Table,</hi> often thinking on it, and often deſiring it, that by enkindling your deſires to <hi>Heavenly Banquets,</hi> you may be indifferent and leſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36870:16"/>Paſſionate for the <hi>Earthly.</hi> Mingle Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes <hi>pious,</hi> or in ſome ſenſe <hi>profitable,</hi> and in all ſenſe; <hi>charitable</hi> and <hi>innocent.</hi> To Conclude, Let your <hi>Drink</hi> ſo ſerve your <hi>Meat,</hi> as your <hi>Meat</hi> doth your <hi>Health,</hi> that it be apt to convey and digeſt it and refreſh the <hi>Spirits,</hi> but let it never go beyond ſuch Refreſhment as may a little lighten the preſent Load of a <hi>Sad</hi> or <hi>Troubled Spirit;</hi> never to <hi>Inconveniency, Lightneſs, Sottiſhneſs, Vanity</hi> or <hi>Intemperance.</hi> Be not Impatiently deſirous of any thing, ſo that you cannot Abſtain from it, for that is to loſe your Liberty and to become a Servant to Meat and Drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Intemperance</hi> is hurtful to <hi>Nature,</hi> by Creating <hi>Diſeaſes;</hi> to your <hi>Good name,</hi> by bringing a <hi>Scandal</hi> on it; and to your <hi>Soul,</hi> by clogging the <hi>Spirits</hi> and hindering it in the Offices of its <hi>Devotion,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Intemperance in Drinking,</hi> a <hi>Vice Deteſtable</hi> in all, but <hi>prodigious</hi> in a <hi>Woman,</hi> who in that caſe puts a double violence upon her <hi>Nature,</hi> the one in the <hi>Intemperance,</hi> the other in the <hi>Immodeſty;</hi> and though ſuch may take their Copy from Men, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Human is ſuch a Beaſt as a <hi>woman</hi> who gives her ſelf every way up to <hi>Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36870:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Affability,</hi> is ſo becoming our Sex, that it is one of their Chiefeſt <hi>Ornaments,</hi> in <hi>Moral Virtues;</hi> and more abſoluely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in them than in Men. As for its <hi>Cauſe,</hi> it derives it ſelf either from a <hi>Native Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Generoſity of Mind,</hi> or from a <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Ingenious Education,</hi> or ſomething joyntly from both; and theſe are as good Originals as any thing Meerly Moral can flow from: And this <hi>Virtue</hi> reaches further, and graſps at that which is <hi>Divine,</hi> for as far as it partakes of <hi>Humility:</hi> it muſt of <hi>Sincerity</hi> alſo, that being a <hi>Virtue</hi> whoſe very Elements are <hi>Plainneſs</hi> and <hi>Simplicity;</hi> for as it has no deſigns that want a cover, ſo it needs none of thoſe Subtilties and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, thoſe Pretences and Artifices requiſite to thoſe that do. 'Tis the Precept of the Apoſtle, Philip. 2.3. <hi>In Lowlyneſs of Mind let each eſteem others better than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Courteſie</hi> and an <hi>Affable Carriage and Behaviour</hi> are ſuch Charms, that they En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear all, but eſpecially your Inferiours, to you, and keep up a Reputation in ſpight of many blemiſhes: A kind Word or Look from a Superiour is ſtrangely taking, and Inſenſibly Steals away the Heart. The <hi>Grecians</hi> comparing the <hi>Affability</hi> and <hi>Eaſie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36870:17"/>Acceſs</hi> of <hi>Cleomene,</hi> with the <hi>Sullen State</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> of other <hi>Princes,</hi> were ſo Enamoured with it, that they judged him only worthy to be their <hi>King;</hi> and as there is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer, ſo alſo no cheaper way of gaining <hi>Love,</hi> and winding into the <hi>Affections</hi> of thoſe you Converſe with: A <hi>Friendly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation</hi> is as eaſie as a <hi>Frown,</hi> or <hi>Reproach;</hi> and that <hi>Kindneſs</hi> may be preſerved by them, which, if once forfeited, will not at a far greater price be recovered. Beſides, when <hi>Viciſſitudes</hi> are conſidered, it may be a Providence to you, the greateſt Perſons, upon the <hi>turns of Fortune,</hi> often ſtand in need of the aſſiſtance of the meaneſt, and then you will be ſure of Friends at need to Comfort you; and Rejoyce that by your <hi>Affability</hi> you have Link'd them to your Intereſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Disdain</hi> is contrary to this, and will not fail to procure you <hi>Enemies,</hi> as it is it ſelf an <hi>enemy to Civil Society</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: Frowns, Haughty Looks, Surly Words, or an expectation of more Cringing and Submiſſion than is due,</hi> cannot be well reliſh'd or digeſted. A <hi>Proud Temper</hi> is hateful to all, eſpecially that are of an <hi>Affable Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> it ſhews the <hi>Birth,</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> mean or poor; and gives a ſuſpicion that it is but a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36870:17"/>
                  <hi>Pageantry</hi> of ſome <hi>Muſhrome</hi> newly ſprung up that ſtands ſo ſtiff. So that inſtead of keeping others at diſtance, this invites them to a nearer inſpection, that if there be any flaw either in their <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Birth,</hi> 'twill be ſure to e diſcovered, there being no ſuch prying Inquiſitor as Curioſity, urged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſenſe of Contempt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Duty of Virgins: Directing them what they ought to Do, and what to Avoid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gaining all the Accompliſhments Requir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in that State. With the Whole Art of Love Being Directions how to Receive the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes either of a Nobleman, Gentleman, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tradeſmen, with that Prudence, as not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be accounted Scornful, Moroſe, or Fond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Whereby Perſons of the Meaneſt Rank, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Raiſe their Fortunes to the higheſt pitch o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Honour and Greatneſs.</head>
               <p>HAving given you an Account of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> General Qualifications which are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> once the <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> of your Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there are notwithſtanding <hi>Specific</hi> differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ariſing from the ſeveral <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:36870:18"/>of <hi>Life,</hi> ſome whereof, may exact <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reater degrees even of the former <hi>Virtues,</hi> and all may have ſome diſtinct or particular Requiſites adapted to that particular State and Condition; and therefore of theſe my purpoſed Method engages me to Conſider in their Order; That is of <hi>Virginity, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> and <hi>Widowhood.</hi> Which as they differ widely from each other, ſo for the diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their reſpective Duties, there are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Cautions worthy to be Adverted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virginity,</hi> or the <hi>Virgin State,</hi> is firſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>der, (the <hi>Infancy</hi> and <hi>Childhood</hi> of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>illingly paſs over, and Addreſs my ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou, when it is ſuppoſed you are at Years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diſcretion; and that may be properly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anted at the Age of <hi>Sixteen,</hi> and ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.) This is that part of Life that claims <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great ſhare of <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> to ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t off with a true Luſtre, but above all <hi>Modeſty,</hi> as it relates to <hi>Chaſtity</hi> and <hi>Decent behaviour,</hi> in which you in this State are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore eſpecially concern'd, for the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame of <hi>Virgin</hi> imports a <hi>Critical Niceneſs</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Point. Every <hi>Indecent Curioſity,</hi> or <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Fancy</hi> is a <hi>Deflowring</hi> of the <hi>Mind;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery the leaſt <hi>Corruption</hi> of them gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me Degrees of <hi>Defilement</hi> to the <hi>Body</hi> too, or between the State of <hi>Pure <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpotted</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36870:18"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chooſing Imployeth an Approving, and if you ſix on any againſt whom the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as given Judgement, 'tis not ſo well na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured as altogether to believe you are <hi>Averſe</hi> to the way of Living they follow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce it doth not Diſcourage you from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itting ſuch into your Boſom Secrets; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt you will be looked upon as a well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſher, if not a partner in their Faults, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou can forgive or ſlightly paſs them over, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not preſumed you be leſs Indulging to our ſelf.</p>
               <p>If it happen after your Engagement, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe you have Contracted Friendſhip with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould Deviate from the Rules of Virtue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou ought however not to be over Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us by ſhew of Belief in the beginning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Diſcovery, but being well informed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Truth, you muſt, without breaking too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oughly, make a fair and quick Retreat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om ſuch miſtaken Acquaintance, leaſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing too trady, the Scandal and Guilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect upon your Good Name and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n: And this is ſo nice a Point, That as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou muſt not be too haſty to joyn in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſure of your Friends,</hi> ſo on the other ſide, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot to Defend them with too much warmth;</hi> or if the Report be True, you will draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ill Appearance upon your ſelf, and it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36870:19"/>will be Conjectured you Plead in this Caſe not without ſome Conſideration to your ſelf; your <hi>Ignorance</hi> may leſſen the <hi>Guilt</hi> but will <hi>improve the Cenſure of the Juſt upon you.</hi> Let the <hi>Good Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe</hi> of thoſE you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Friendſhip with, be a chief Ingredie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in your Choice of them, elſe let your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation be never ſo clear, it may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Clouded by their Faults.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cenſure</hi> is to be avoided as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be, either by you on others, or in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo that you give no Occaſion for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And before you give it on others, let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe of it be conſidered, and then you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to give Sentence as a Majeſtrate, or as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you had ſpecial Authority to beſtow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your Diſcretion, <hi>a good or an ill Name;</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when you do it, dwell not too long upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but give a gentle touch and ſo paſs it over unleſs you can do good by it, in Reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Vice</hi> and promoting the ways of <hi>Virtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and this muſt be done as privately as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be, leſt the Party Judging Uncharitable of your Intentions, <hi>runs into worſe Occaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Scandal,</hi> and it Reflect upon your fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> making your ill-timed Reproaches. A <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſtuck with Thorns</hi> is too rough for the Age, and therefore it muſt, to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more pleaſing, be Adorned with ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:36870:19"/>Flowers, or elſe in theſe particulars it will be unwillingly Entertained; ſo that where it may be ſit to ſtrike, do it as Eaſily and Gentle as you can, do it <hi>in the Tenderneſs of our Sex,</hi> and ſo you may aſſure your ſelves, That where you care to do it, you will wound them more, and do leſs Hurt to your ſelf, by a gentle Stroak, than by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Harſh and Violent; Be therefore quick in ſeeing Faults, that you may avoid them in your ſelf, but ſlow in Expoſing them: You are in this, as in all other Caſes, to conſider the Inviſible thing called <hi>a good Name,</hi> it is made up of the Breath of Numbers that ſpeak well of you, ſo that if by a Diſobliging Word you ſilence the Meaneſt, the Gale which is to bear up your Eſteem will loſe of its Strength, and let it a little flag; and though nothing is ſo vain as the two earneſt purſuit of Empty Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, yet to be kindly Uſed and well thought on by the World, is like a Glory above a Womans Head; it's like a Perfume that Scents where-ever ſhe goeth; it is a Charm againſt Spight and Ill-will; Malice may empty her Quiver without Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for without the conſent of the World, a Scandal doth not go deep, it is only a ſlight ſtroak upon the injured Party,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36870:20"/>Returning with greater force upon the Inflictor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behaviour</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> in this you muſt take <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> along with you for your Guard: Be Vigilent and Cautions, becauſe in this particular you will have many Eyes upon you, and therefore it muſt incline ſtrangely towards the Reſerved Part, yet not altogether Excluding a mixture of Freedom, ſo far as it may be Innocent and Seaſonably Tim'd; yet if you find this makes your Carriage ſubject to Cenſure, you muſt in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure reſtrain it; for if you ſee the Danger at never ſo great a diſtance, you are at that time to ſhorten the <hi>Line of Liberty;</hi> for if you allow your ſelf to go to the extent of every thing that is Lawful, you are ſo very near going farther, that thoſE who lie at Watch will begin to count upon you, Mankind, from the double Temptation of <hi>Vanity</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> being very ready to Conſtrue <hi>every thing a VVoman doth to the hopeful ſide;</hi> and few will make an Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent attempt till they have ſome Glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of Incouragement. It's more ſafe therefore to prevent ſuch forwardneſs, than to go about to Cure it; becauſe from the firſt Allowances it gathereth ſtrength,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36870:20"/>and ſo claims a Right from having been at any time ſuffered without Impunity. Therefore in all your <hi>Converſation</hi> avoid ſuch a <hi>Civility</hi> as may, in this matter, be taken for an <hi>Invitation.</hi> Beward how you bring a Cloud upon your Reputation, in giving way to that which many Women call <hi>an Innocent Liberty or Freedom;</hi> for there are many of our Sex that will be very ready to help on the leaſt appearance that giveth a Handle to be ill Turn'd. They will not be diſpleaſed to Improve their own Value at the loſs of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, when there is a fair occaſion given, for it diſtinguiſhes them the more, Exalts their Credit higher, and, like a Picture ſet off with Shades, they ſeem Fairer when they make your Actions to be leſs innocent than theirs; and it ſeems to them, That their load of infamy is leſſen'd by throwing part of it upon others: So that they will not only <hi>Improve</hi> when it lieth in their way, but take pains to <hi>Find out</hi> the leaſt Miſtake <hi>an Innocent Woman Committeth,</hi> in Revenge of the ſuppoſed Injury ſhe does, in leading a Life which is <hi>a Reproach to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, even to the other Sex, you muſt ſhun <hi>Illbred Affected ſhineſs,</hi> nor uſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36870:21"/>an unſuitable Roughneſs to your own; for theſe are unneceſſary to your Vertue. But you muſt take up a way of Living, that may prevent all courſe Raileries, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly Freedoms; carry Looks that may forbid without Rudeneſs, and Oblige with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Invitation: But this is ſo very Nice that it muſt Engage you to have a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual watch upon your <hi>Eyes,</hi> That no care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Glances give more Advantage that Words, for thoſe may be thrown out a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> random, and bear doubtful meanings: but Men look on the <hi>Eyes</hi> as the <hi>Hearts Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters,</hi> and gather more Aſſurance from them of Encouragement, than from the <hi>Tongue,</hi> their Language being more ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant and obſervable to Men.</p>
               <p>Your <hi>Civility,</hi> which muſt be always preſerved, muſt not by any means be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to a <hi>Compliance,</hi> which may Betray you into irrecoverable Miſtakes; for the doubtful word <hi>Compliance</hi> has lead more of our Sex into blame than all other things, carrying them by degrees, into a thing called <hi>a good kind Woman, an Eaſie, Idle Creature, that bath neither Good nor Ill but by Chance,</hi> not having Judgment or Choice, but leaveth thoſe to the Company ſhe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes withall to frame and determine for her.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36870:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diverſion</hi> is an eaſement and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the Toiles of Live; a Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Mind.</hi> But then it muſt be Moderate and Suitable, not too Eager in the purſuit of Pleaſure; for that, whilſt you are young, is Dangerous, and to catch at it in Riper Years, is graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Shadow; for then, being leſs Natural, it grows Indecent; and indeed though you ſuppoſe you have it, you will find your miſtake, or at leaſt cannot hold it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diverſions</hi> are the moſt properly apply'd to Eaſe, and Relieves (as I have hinted) thoſe that are oppreſſed by being too much Imploy'd. Thoſe that are Idle have leſs need of them, though above all others they are moſt given to them. To Unbend our Thoughts when they are overſtretched by too much Care, is not more Natural than it is neceſſary: But to turn your whole Life into one large Holiday, not only palls the Pleaſure, but renders you Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Mind</hi> as well as the <hi>Body</hi> is tired by being always in one poſture, too Serious Breaketh, and too Diverting Looſneth it; 'tis only variety that giveth the Savoury Reliſh; a frequent repetition grows firſt to Indifferency, and after that becomes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36870:22"/>but whilſt they are well choſen and well timed, they cannot be blameable, yet to make your ſelf cheap by tiring others with your Diverſion, in one of the meaneſt things that can be done.</p>
               <p>To Play ſometimes to Entertaim Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, or to Divert your ſelf, is not to be Diſallowed; but to do it often, to be call'd a Gameſter, is utterly to be avoided, next to the things that are Criminal. It Engages you to a habit of Idleneſs; and ill Hours Introduce you into ill mix'd Company, whilſt you neglect your Civilities abroad, and your Buſineſs at home, draw you to Acquaintance that will not be for your Credit. And indeed if you ſhould ſee your own Faces upon an ill Game, at a deep Stake, you would certainly deſiſt from any thing that could put your Looks under ſuch a diſadvantage.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Dance,</hi> or <hi>Play</hi> on any ſuitable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of <hi>Muſick</hi> is commendable; but, in the firſt place, Remember the end of your Learning of it was, That you might the better know to move Gracefully, for it is only an advantage ſo far, and when it goeth beyond it, one may call it <hi>Excelling in Muſick,</hi> which is no great Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. As for the latter, it is to Delight
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36870:22"/>the Sadneſs of the Mind, and Tune over Melancholy Hours; but be careful not to do theſe often, becauſe you do them well; the eaſieſt and ſafeſt Method is to do it in Private Company, amongſt particular Friends, and then Careleſly like a Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and not with Study and solemnity, as if it was a Buſineſs, or your ſelf over much Affected with it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bebaviour to Superiors,</hi> &amp;c. As to theſe in the firſt place, you muſt render what is ſeemly, that is, ſuch Civility and Oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſpectfulneſs, as may win upon them, not only to Eſteem you, but rank you among the number of their Friends, and ſpeak well of your deportment and demeanor, as one of an Ingenious Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and good Parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Equals</hi> muſt be treated with all <hi>Civility</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> the occaſion requires, leſt you be reflected on, as <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> A young <hi>Lady,</hi> or <hi>Gentlewoman,</hi> will find a great uneaſineſs in converſation, if ſhe appear ſolli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itous to ingroſs reſpect to her ſelf: You therefore ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a reaſonable diſtribution, and allow it to others, that you may have it returned to you. You muſt not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomly <hi>Nice,</hi> nor diſcover your ſelf to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36870:23"/>be too <hi>Delicate,</hi> as <hi>if ordinary things were too courſe for you:</hi> This is <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmannerly and an Offenſive</hi> Price; and where it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Practiſed, deſerves to be Mortified, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which indeed it ſeldom fails. You are not to lean too much upon your Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but ſeem rather mean in your ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Opinion, that others may exalt you; you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fame founding far more ſweeter in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mouths of others, than in your own.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inferiours</hi> expect <hi>Courteſie</hi> and <hi>Obliging Condeſcenſions</hi> towards them; and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all the good offices you can it will much endear them to you: And indeed, this many times keeps up a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in ſpight of <hi>Blemiſhes.</hi> A kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Word, or pleaſing Look from a Superiour is ſtrangely Charming; and rivets their Affections to you: Which conſideration made the Wiſe Man <hi>Prefer a good Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Before a Gift.</hi> It is a cheap way of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Love.</hi> A <hi>Frown,</hi> or a <hi>Reproach,</hi> put you to more trouble than <hi>good Words,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an <hi>affable ſmiling Temper.</hi> It was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a good <hi>Emperor</hi> in this caſe, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be would ſo entertain the Addreſes of his Subjects, as if he were a Subject, he would wiſh the Prince ſhould entertain him;</hi> a <hi>Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> very worthy to ſway all perſons, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36870:23"/>thoſe of Honour, in their entercourſe with others. And when you meet with a cold neglectful treatment from any above you, examine your own reſentments, and then reflect, <hi>That if you give the like to thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elow you, they will doubtleſs have the ſame Senſe;</hi> and therefore reſolve never to offer, what you do ſo much diſlike to bear; and when you do thus, ſuch Inferiours will convert an <hi>Injury</hi> into a <hi>Benefit.</hi> You will <hi>Civilize</hi> your ſelf by the <hi>Rudeneſs</hi> of others, and make that ill Nature your own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>line. Some indeed, make <hi>Quality</hi> an <hi>Idol,</hi> and then their <hi>Reaſon</hi> muſt fall down and <hi>Worſhip it.</hi> They would have the World think, that no amends can be made for the want of a great <hi>Title,</hi> or an ancient <hi>Coat of Arms.</hi> They imagine, that with theſe advantages they ſtand upon the higher Ground, which maketh them look down on <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> as things inferiour to them. This miſtake is not only ſenſleſs, but criminal too, in putting a greater-price upon that, which is a piece of <hi>Good Luck,</hi> that upon things which are valuable in themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:36870:24"/>
               <head>The whole Art of LOVE</head>
               <p>HAving underſtood and duly weighed theſe things with the former <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> and <hi>Accompliſhments</hi> both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Moral,</hi> I ſuppoſe yon now at years capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of entering into the <hi>Holy State of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony,</hi> Ordained at firſt by God in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice,</hi> and ſince not only in <hi>Sacred Writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> but highly eſteemed by all the <hi>Civilize<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nations.</hi> And that you may not ruſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo weighty a thing raſhly, or unad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, I ſhall (to conclude the <hi>Virgin</hi>-ſtate, lay down ſome <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Directions,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not only be a ſure and ſafe Conduct to ſuch as are placed in ſtations of <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency,</hi> but even to thoſe of Lower <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees:</hi> ſo that the meaneſt may raiſe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fortune by them; For I have often ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, through Cautions and Pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Management in matters of Love, many Poor <hi>Virgins,</hi> Initiated into Families by <hi>Marriage,</hi> that have not barely enriched them, but given ſuch Reputation and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to their <hi>Virtues,</hi> that they have out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhined thoſe, that a little before lookes down upon them with <hi>Diſdain &amp; Contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:36870:24"/>upon examination it will be found, that Nature is to far from being unjuſt to us, that ſhe is partial on our ſide; and for the ſeeming injuſtice has made large a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for one other advantage, the right of complaining by that means being come over to us, it is in our power, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to free our ſelves, but to ſubdue our Maſters; and without Violence throw both their <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Legal Authority</hi> at our Feet: The <hi>Sexes</hi> are made of different tempers, that the <hi>Defects</hi> may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſupplied, by mutual aſſiſtance. Our <hi>Sex</hi> wants the others <hi>Reaſon</hi> for our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> and their <hi>Strength</hi> for our <hi>protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Their want our <hi>Gentleneſs</hi> to <hi>Soften</hi> and <hi>Entertain</hi> them, our <hi>Looks</hi> have more <hi>Strength</hi> than their <hi>Laws;</hi> there is more power in our <hi>Tears,</hi> than in their <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments;</hi> and therefore things prudently managed, will by degrees, bring over a <hi>Husband</hi> to ſee his <hi>Errors;</hi> and by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his failings, take care for the future, to amend them; but then the <hi>Wifes Gentleneſs</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Mirror.</hi> wherein he muſt ſee the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of his <hi>Irregularities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Something more muſt be ſaid in this point, in the <hi>Conduct of your Behaviour
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:36870:25"/>to his Relations and Friends:</hi> For many times a neglect, or ſlight regard of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> makes wide breaches in a Family: Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be ſure they will not fail to reſent any ſenſible diſreſpect, and complaints: O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will not always fail to ſtir up your <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Anger</hi> againſt you, eſpecially when he concludes himſelf injured by it: And therefore you muſt conſider to carry you ſelf even with them; for the Family in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which you are ingraffed, will gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally be apt to expect, that like a <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in a Forreign Country, you ſhould in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> great meaſure conform to their methods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they are of any conſiderable degree; and not bring in a new Model, by your own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority:</hi> And therefore that you may with the leſs difficulty afterwards give your Directions, you ought to take them firſt from your Husbands Friends, if an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity offers, gain them by early ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to them, and they will be ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that as nothing is more thankful than <hi>Pride,</hi> when it is complyed with that they will ſtrive which of them ſhall moſt recommend to you; and when they have contributed to your taking firm root in your <hi>Husbands</hi> good <hi>Opinion,</hi> you will have the leſs dependance on theirs, though
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:36870:25"/>you ought not to neglect any reaſonable means of preſerving it. Conſider where a <hi>Husband</hi> is Governed as it were by his Friends, he is eaſily inflamed by them; and he that is not ſo, will notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his own ſake expect to have them conſidered, it is eaſily improved to a point of Honour in a <hi>Husband,</hi> not to have his <hi>Relations</hi> neglected: and nothing is found more dangerous in this kind, than to raiſe an objection grounded on <hi>Pride;</hi> it is the moſt ſtubborn and laſting paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage we are ſubject to, and where it begins a <hi>War,</hi> it is very hard to make a ſecure <hi>Peace:</hi> therefore uſe them well, and be well with them, and they will not fail to ſupport you in your <hi>Husbands Love;</hi> and then if <hi>Diſcontents</hi> ariſe, it is your own fault.</p>
               <p>The next thing I am to lay down in the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Marriage,</hi> is, <hi>The Office and Duty of a</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mother:</hi> And this may be branched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many ſeverals; but many of them being not very ſignificant, I ſhall only reduce them under two Heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Care.</hi> A <hi>Mother</hi> is a Title of ſo much tenderneſs, that we find it borrowed by our common Dialect to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:36870:26"/>expreſs the tendereſt of all kindneſſes So that Nature ſeems ſufficient to have ſecured the <hi>Love of a Mother</hi> toward the <hi>Fruit</hi> of her <hi>Womb,</hi> without the ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of any poſitive Law, unleſs where <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in <hi>VVickedneſs,</hi> and that very ſeldom give contrary precedents, to the Blot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Name, Abhorrence, and laſting Infam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> The <hi>Love</hi> of a <hi>Parent,</hi> however the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> may afterward prove, ought, and indeed naturally is deſcending, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things move moſt violently downwards So that whereas, that of <hi>Children</hi> to their <hi>Parents,</hi> commonly need a Spur, this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Mother</hi> frequently requires a <hi>Bridl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who by ſtrength of <hi>Feminine</hi> paſſion, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exceeds the <hi>Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore to regulate this <hi>Affection</hi> you are to Advert to theſe two Rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That you hurt not your ſelf by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That you hurt not your Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the firſt you are in danger, if you ſuffer that human Affection to ſwell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its Banks, ſo as to come in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with the Divine, for then you diſhonour God by making an Idol o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your <hi>Child;</hi> and for this cauſe, <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs</hi> is in one ſenſe called <hi>Idolatry,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:36870:26"/>what any one ſets his or her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon entirely, he or ſhe is ſuppoſed to <hi>Idolize,</hi> and frame it in their Imaginations as a <hi>God,</hi> though in reality, it be nothing ſo; and I cannot but fear, God, upon this account, has been diſpleaſed with too many Mothers, and ſent them <hi>Afflictions</hi> even to <hi>Humbling,</hi> by (as in ſome Sence I may term it) untimely taking from them thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren they <hi>Idolized,</hi> to the prejudice of his Honour, and even of their own Souls; for indeed every thing is ſo accounted, that <hi>Rivals the Love of God in our Hearts;</hi> and he who owns the Title of a <hi>Jealous God,</hi> cannot be reaſonably thought to bear it, without one way or other Puniſhing us.</p>
               <p>By this however I do not mean you ſhould follow the Example of thoſe, who immoderatly love their own pleaſure, and do not in the leaſt regard their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, (which God has given them as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Bleſſings) looking on them as a <hi>Clog,</hi> to keep them within doors; and think their Adverting to them will hinder their <hi>Gadding Abroad;</hi> turning them over (for that Reaſon, which indeed is but a very ſlender one) to the Care of a <hi>Nurſe,</hi> or a <hi>Maid,</hi> whilſt perhaps a <hi>Dog</hi> or <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cy,</hi> as thought worthy <hi>their own Attend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce.</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:36870:27"/>This is too much in the extream of the other ſide, and ſeems beyond the Bowel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a <hi>Motherly Tenderneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as to the former Matter, whether <hi>Beautiful</hi> or <hi>Homely,</hi> make no different in your <hi>Maternal Care</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe they proceed from you, and it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the power of the <hi>Infant</hi> to Form it Self but it is formed in the Womb, by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wonderful working of Almighty God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Shaped as he pleaſes: And many times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mend the Defect, <hi>a Diſtorted Body, Rump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in the cells of Nature,</hi> is Endowed with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Beautiful Soul,</hi> when that Caſt in a Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Mould, to outward appearance, is an <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or like a Picture, only repreſenting a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> portion and Statute to the Eye, witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Intellectual Faculties</hi> to make it what it R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> preſents.</p>
               <p>In this caſe a <hi>Mother</hi> that pretends<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Virtue,</hi> muſt make no difference, but div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her <hi>Affections</hi> equally, yet ſo that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be Moderate, and not infringe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Love ſhe owes her Maker. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the acts of the Soul are conſidred, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be no Competitor in Affection with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mighty, but he muſt be all all, as to <hi>Divine Love,</hi> for he is the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unlimited Object of it; and if you ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:36870:27"/>in this, you hurt your ſelf, and bring on his Wrath, in Puniſhment here, and if not Repented of, perhaps Eternally hereafter.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as I have already hinted, you hurt your Children in not bringing them up in due Obedience and Reſpect towards you, whereas, when you generally Dote upon all, or more particularly on one, it cannot be brought to paſs, for then, through want of that, ſtrict Government which in many caſes is required, and an over Indulgence will not permit you to exceriſe your ſelf, nor you others to do it, they will, without a wonderful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, grow <hi>Stubborn</hi> and <hi>headſtrong</hi> as they grow in years. The only Juſtifiable ground of partiality, if you ſingle out any of the number of your Children as a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite,</hi> muſt be <hi>Virtue,</hi> and this muſt only extend top provoke a <hi>Virtuous Emulation</hi> in the reſt; and then you muſt ſo manage it, as to evidence it is no inequality in your own inclination, but meerly the force of the others <hi>Deſerts;</hi> not the <hi>Perſon</hi> of your Child, but the <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that Biaſſes you; and when <hi>Virtue</hi> is known to be the only <hi>Ingratiating Quality,</hi> the reſt may labour perhaps to become yours and Gods <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites.</hi> Therefore ſhew them early an
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:36870:28"/>Example of <hi>Piety,</hi> in your own Life and Converſation: And in the Decorum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Family keep them out of the hearing of <hi>Vain Words,</hi> or any thing that may ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Vitiate</hi> their tender Years, by which they are too apt to take deeply the firſt impreſſion of Words or Actions, not by time ſo eaſily Obliterated as may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined. And in matters of the Virtuous Education of your children, you are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only Accountable to your Self, but God He ſeems to ſay to you, as King <hi>Pharoabs</hi> Daughter did to the Mother o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Moſes, Take this Child and Nurſe it for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> The end for which he gives them, is, That they ſhould be brought up <hi>in his Fear,</hi> that they may Live, Grow up, and Dey <hi>in his Favour:</hi> And then you may have the Comfort of meeting them again in an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Eternity</hi> of Bleſſedneſs, nevermore t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be Separated: And this will certainly add to thoſe Joys, that in themſelves are very Excellent, <hi>That you have Brought forth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Trained up Children to Live and Reign wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt in his Kingdom of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The beſt way of approving your Love towards them is, by the <hi>Duty of Care</hi> Without this, all the moſt Paſſionate Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Kindneſs are but an Airy Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:36870:28"/>a Fantaſtical Scene, and will no more advantage a Child, than the Picture of Food will Nouriſn it. Nor is this <hi>Care</hi> a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, Momentary <hi>Duty,</hi> but it muſt be taken through the ſeveral <hi>Stages</hi> of <hi>Infancy, Childhood,</hi> and <hi>Youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe is a ſeaſon only for thoſe Cares that concern the <hi>Bodies</hi> of your Children. Providing for their careful Attendance, and all other things condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to Strengthen their Conſtitutions; laying a foundation for future Health and Vigour; which is your Intereſt not only upon the <hi>Body,</hi> but upon an <hi>Intelectual</hi> account: The good <hi>Temprature</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> being a great <hi>Aid</hi> towardss the free operation of the <hi>Mind.</hi> But this <hi>Health</hi> is not always the conſequent of a <hi>Nice Breeding,</hi> for that many times overthrows it, when Inuring them to <hi>Moderate Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> ſeldom fails of giving a <hi>Strong</hi> ad <hi>Healthful Conſtitution.</hi> Too much <hi>Feeding</hi> and <hi>Delicacies</hi> breed <hi>Humours,</hi> by reaſon of a weak Digeſtion, to which moſt children in their Infancy are ſubject; and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundance of Humours breeding Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, which often become Habitual, or too ſadly end in an Early Death, when moderate Feeding, and expoſing them to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:36870:29"/>the freſh Air abroad, and not Mewing, or as it were <hi>Stifling them in a Nurſery,</hi> gives them ſtrength and Refreſhment; for when Nature is not over-loaded, ſhe makes a due <hi>Digeſtion,</hi> which turns to Sweet and wholſome Blood, and kindly Humours; but being over-loaded or oppreſſed, ſhe is in a manner <hi>Suffocated,</hi> and cannot exerciſe her <hi>Function</hi> to proper advantages: And as for a <hi>free breathing Air,</hi> refin'd from <hi>Damps</hi> and <hi>Groceneſs,</hi> it rarifies the <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Spirits,</hi> and is <hi>the great refreſher of Life.</hi> But of theſe I ſhall Speak more, when I come to Treat of <hi>Ordering Children,</hi> as to their <hi>Health</hi> in <hi>Diet</hi> and <hi>Phyſical matters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when they are paſt <hi>Infancy,</hi> if you <hi>Dote</hi> ſo as to <hi>Hoodwink you ſelf,</hi> becauſe you will not See their <hi>Faults,</hi> or <hi>Manacle your Hands</hi> that you cannot <hi>Chaſtiſe</hi> them, then it will be Imputed your <hi>Fault</hi> if their <hi>Vices</hi> grow up with them; and you will find little comfort of them in the end, tho' you promiſe your ſelf never ſo much in lieu of your kindneſs towards them; For when the Mothers Affections are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbridled,</hi> the Childs will be ſo too. The wiſe Man, in this caſe, gives you better advice, <hi>viz. Bow down the Neck of a Child from its Youth,</hi> that is, bring it up to ſtrict rules of <hi>Virtue</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:36870:29"/>and put a <hi>Bridle</hi> on its Stubborn Iuclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and ſo when it grows up it will Bleſs you, not only as its <hi>Parent,</hi> but <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver;</hi> and <hi>Secure</hi> to it the <hi>future Happineſs of Life.</hi> For if you permit them to run on in their own <hi>Vain Devices,</hi> in hopes time may alter it, by making them ſee their Folly and grow Wiſer, you will be too often miſerably miſtaken, for as their Joynts knit and gather ſtrength, ſo do their <hi>Ill Habits,</hi> till at laſt they are Confirmed in an <hi>Obſtinacy;</hi> and by that means you ſet them in a perfect oppoſition to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern they ſhould Imitate. For as <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Childhood increaſed in <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and the <hi>Divine Favour, Luke</hi> 2. ſo will theirs in all thoſe <hi>Provoking Follies</hi> which may Avert both the Love of God and Man. And then alas what recompence can the little Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhments and Careſſes of a Mother make her Children, for ſuch important, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable <hi>Miſchief?</hi> So that if you would be really Kind, you muſt temper your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence with a <hi>Prudent Severity,</hi> or elſe you eminently violate this Second Rule, by which you ſhould Regulate you Love, and ſo do that to them which <hi>Jacob</hi> feared from his Father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. <hi>Bring a Curſe upon them and not a Bleſſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:36870:30"/>
               <p>Thirdly, In the next Period of their time, when they are arrived at Years of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Growth,</hi> Then you may be more Familiar with them, they having before been Seaſoned to know their <hi>Diſtance</hi> and <hi>Duty.</hi> Allow them ſuch a Kind, yet Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Freedom, that they may have a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſancy in your Converſation, and not be tempted to ſeek it amongſt their Inferiours. That the belief of your kindneſs may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant the pretenſions of thoſe mean <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants,</hi> who by little Flatteries, endeavour to ſcrew themſelves into their good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and become their Confidents; than which, eſpecially to <hi>Daughters,</hi> there is nothing more Miſchieveous, in teaching them <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> and rendering them <hi>Mutinous againſt their Parents,</hi> by buzzing into their Ears the wild notions of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Liberty and Freedom,</hi> which Lectures they ſhould not ſo ſoon be truſted withall. Beſides, thoſe <hi>Intimacies</hi> are often Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions to worſe; many <hi>Scandalous Amours,</hi> and <hi>unequal Matches</hi> have had their riſe from them. It muſt therefore be your Buſineſs to prevent all ſuch <hi>pernicious Leagues,</hi> in preingaging them in more ſafe Familiarities, either with your ſelf, or ſome others, of whoſe <hi>Virtues</hi> you have reaſon to be Confident.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:36870:30"/>
               <p>But the moſt Infalible Security againſt this, and all other Miſchiefs, is, <hi>to bring them to an Intimacy and Converſation with their Maker,</hi> by fixing a true ſenſe of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in their <hi>Souls;</hi> for if that can effectually be done, it will ſuperſced all other Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients; for if they duly conſider they are always <hi>in Gods Preſence,</hi> they will want no other <hi>Inſpector;</hi> nor much need <hi>Monitors,</hi> if they ſeriouſly attend to the advice of their own <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Neither will it tend only to the ſecuring of their <hi>Innocency;</hi> but their <hi>Reputation;</hi> it being one part of the <hi>Chriſtian Law, to Abſtain from all appearances of Evil,</hi> 1. Theſ. 5.22. <hi>To do things that are of Good Report,</hi> Phil. 4.8. So that <hi>Piety</hi> is the only <hi>Compleat Armour,</hi> to defend at once their <hi>Virtue</hi> and their <hi>Fame;</hi> and it is extreamly neceſſary they ſhould be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with it, at this Age eſpecially.</p>
               <p>It is ſad to be Conſidered indeed, That ſome <hi>Mothers</hi> neglect this moſt Important Concern in their <hi>Daughters,</hi> though Nicely Curious in their other parts of Breeding, They give them <hi>Civil Accompliſhments,</hi> but no <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> thoſe are excluded by them out of the <hi>Scheme of Education;</hi> and by that means lye under the prejudice of being not only <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary,</hi> but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngentile,</hi> below the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:36870:31"/>regard of a <hi>Perſon of Quality.</hi> I ſuppoſe this is often encreaſed by a little <hi>Vanity</hi> they have in ſeeing them excel in ſome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe <hi>Exteriour Qualities,</hi> which may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to the <hi>Humour of the World</hi> upon the Improving whereof they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> intent, that more Material things are over looked. And ſo this part of the <hi>Buſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Duty of a Wife,</hi> I ſhall Conclude in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing you to be careful in Placing, or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing your Children in the World either in <hi>Marriage,</hi> or <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> that the may Flouriſh in <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Wealth;</hi> and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the laſting Comforts of your Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Miſtreſs</hi> is another <hi>Obligation</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on you when <hi>Marry'd,</hi> if you Live in any Quality or Repute in the World; for in ſuch a caſe the Inſpection of the Family is uſually your Province; for though you are not <hi>Supream</hi> there, yet you are to improve your <hi>Delegated Authority</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Advantage of them under it; And you more <hi>Conſtant Reſidence</hi> gives you more op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of it, than the frequent <hi>Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> of your <hi>Husband</hi> will perhaps allow him. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets this as the <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Indiſpenable Duty</hi> of a <hi>Married Woman That ſhe Guide the Houſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Not thinking it a Point of Greatneſs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:36870:31"/>remit the Mannagement of all <hi>Domeſtick Concerns</hi> to a <hi>Mercenary Houſekeeper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, as to your well Guiding of your Houſe, I know no better <hi>Rule</hi> Than <hi>that you endeavour to make all that are yours to be Gods Servants alſo.</hi> This will ſecure you of all thoſe Intermedial Qualifications in them, in which your <hi>Secular Intereſt</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, their own <hi>Conſciences</hi> being the beſt <hi>Spy</hi> you can ſet upon them, as to their <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Fidelity;</hi> and alſo the Beſt <hi>Spur</hi> to <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Dilligence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Chriſtian Family ſhould be the Epitomy of a Church,</hi> It is not only the <hi>Duty</hi> but <hi>Intereſt,</hi> of all that have Families, to keep up the <hi>Eſteem</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> in them. It was one of the greateſt Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Abraham</hi> to God, <hi>That be would Command his Houſhould to keep the way of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 18.19. And <hi>Joſhua</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes no leſs for the <hi>Piety</hi> of his Houſe than himſelf, <hi>As for me</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and my Houſe, we will Serve the Lord,</hi> Joſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5. But when <hi>Pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is planted in a Family, it will ſoon wither, if it be not kept in Vigor by Diſcipline: This you muſt promoreby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your own Example to your Servants, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them to mind their <hi>Duty to God;</hi> and obſerve they do not neglect it, or do it
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:36870:32"/>
                  <hi>Hypocritically,</hi> for Form and Compliance only which may be diſcerned in their Converſations elſewhere.</p>
               <p>You muſt Remember not to fall into Miſtakes, of thinking becauſe they receive Wages, and are ſo Inferiour to you, they are therefore beneath your Care, to know how to Mannage them. They are the moving <hi>Engines</hi> of your Family, and let your Directions be never ſo faultleſs, yet if they <hi>Stop,</hi> or <hi>Move Irregular,</hi> the whole Order of the Houſe will be at a ſtand, or diſcompoſed. Beſides, the Inequality which is between you, muſt not make you forget that Nature maketh no ſuch diſtinction: But that <hi>Servants</hi> ought at leaſt to be looked upon as <hi>humble Freinds;</hi> and that good uſage, and returns of kindneſs, are as much due to thoſe that deſerve it, as their Service is due to you when you require it. A <hi>Fooliſh Haughtineſs</hi> in the <hi>Stile of Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or in the manner of <hi>Commanding</hi> them, is in it ſelf very unſeemly, and frequently begets averſion in them, of which the leaſt ill effect to be expected is, That they will be ſlow and careleſs in all you Enjoyn them: And by Experience you will find it true, That you will be ſo much the more Obeyed, as you are the leſs Imperious.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:36870:32"/>
               <p>Be not too <hi>haſty</hi> in giving your Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> not too <hi>angry</hi> when they are not altogether obſerved; much leſs be not <hi>Lowd,</hi> or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear too much <hi>Diſturbed:</hi> An evenneſs in diſtinguiſhing when they do <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi> will make them move by a <hi>Rule,</hi> and without <hi>Noiſe;</hi> and will the better ſet out your <hi>Skill</hi> in Conducting matters with <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Silence.</hi> Let there be well choſen hours for the inſpecting of <hi>Houſhould Affairs,</hi> which may be diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of your time, that the <hi>neceſſary Cares</hi> may come in their proper place, without any influence upon your <hi>good Humour,</hi> or interruption to other things. By theſe Methods you will put your ſelf into a condition of being valued by your Servants; and you need not doubt but their Obedience will natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally follow.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Art of laying out of Money Wiſely;</hi> muſt be one of your greateſt Cares; it is not attained without conſiderable <hi>Thought;</hi> and it is yet more difficult in the caſe of a <hi>Wife,</hi> who is accountable to her <hi>Husband</hi> for hir Miſtakes in it. In this therefore you are to keep a Mean, between the two Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams of <hi>Profuſeneſs</hi> and a <hi>Niggardly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> and if you cannot hold the <hi>Ballance</hi> even, let it encline rather towards the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:36870:33"/>ſide,</hi> as more ſuitable to your Quality, and leſs ſubject to <hi>Reproach.</hi> A little <hi>Money</hi> miſpent is ſooner recovered, than the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit which is loſt by having it unhandſomly ſaved; and a prudent <hi>Husband</hi> will leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give a ſhamefull piece of <hi>Parſimony,</hi> than a little <hi>Extravagancy,</hi> if it be not too often repeated. Give no juſt cauſe to the meaneſt Servant you entertain, to complain of the want of any thing that is neceſſary. Above all six it in your Thoughts, as an <hi>unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Maxim,</hi> That nothing is truly <hi>Fine,</hi> but what is <hi>Fit,</hi> and that juſt what is proper for your Circumſtances, of their ſeveral kinds, is much finer than all you can add to it: For thoſe that break through theſe Bounds, Launch into the wide Sea of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy;</hi> and then every thing will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Neceſſary, becauſe they have a mind to it; not ſo properly, becauſe it is fit, but becauſe ſome body elſe has it. This Ladies <hi>Logick</hi> ſets <hi>Reaſon</hi> with its Heels upwards, by carrying the <hi>Rule</hi> from <hi>Things</hi> to <hi>Perſons,</hi> and Appealing from what is <hi>Right,</hi> to every <hi>Fool</hi> that is in the <hi>Wrong.</hi> Rememnber <hi>That Children and Fools want every thing that they See,</hi> becauſe they have not Wit to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh what is reaſonably neceſſary: And therefore there is no ſtronger Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:36870:33"/>of a <hi>Crazy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> than mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too large a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of things <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> when indeed there are ſo very few that have a right to be placed in it. Let your Judgment firſt make a Tryal of every thing, before you allow it a place in your <hi>Deſire,</hi> elſe your <hi>Husband</hi> may conceive it as neceſſary to <hi>Deny,</hi> as it is for you to <hi>Crave</hi> what ever is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable;</hi> and if you ſhould too often give him that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, its ten to one but the habit of refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, may reach to things that are not unfit for you</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Duty of a</hi> WIDOW.</head>
               <p>THE State that ſuceeds that of Mariage, is Widowhood, which though it ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedes thoſe Duties which are terminated immediatly in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the deceaſed <hi>Husband,</hi> yet endears thoſe that may be paid to his <hi>Aſhes, For Love is ſtreng as Death,</hi> Cant. 8.6. And therefore where it is pure and genuine, cannot be extinguiſhed but by Death. It Burns like the <hi>Funeral Lamps</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:36870:34"/>of old, even in <hi>Charnel-Houſes and Vaults.</hi> The <hi>Conjugal Love</hi> (tranſplanted into the <hi>Grave,</hi> as into a finer Mould) improves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Piety;</hi> and lays a kind of Sacred Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on the <hi>Widow</hi> to perform every Office of Reſpect which his <hi>Remains</hi> are capable of. And this may be Conſidered in a Threefold Manner, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>To His Body.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>His Memory.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>His Children.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Firſt,</hi> it muſt be in giving it an honourable and decent <hi>Interment,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Quality he Lived in; this being a very commendable Reſpect to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed: Yet it muſt be ſo proportioned, that your Reſpect to the Dead, may not Injure a Nobler <hi>Relique</hi> of him <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>Children,</hi> by an <hi>Expenſive Extravagancy,</hi> beyond what he leaves will properly bear. And in the Loſs to Carry you ſelf with Decency, and a Modeſt Sorrow; not by a frantick exceſs of <hi>Grief</hi> to deſtroy your Health, or putting your ſelf out of a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of minding your affairs, ſince by ſuch a Separation a double Care is reuolved on you: Some that have expreſſed ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Paſſionate Sorrow, have rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced themſelves by it, than it turned to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:36870:34"/>any Advantage to them, by letting thoſe Thoughts too ſoon Vaniſh in a <hi>Second Marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The more Valuable Kindneſs is therefore his <hi>Memory,</hi> which you muſt endeavour to <hi>Embalm,</hi> and keep from <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing:</hi> And as the Cuſtom holds, not to <hi>Embalm</hi> without <hi>Odours;</hi> ſo you are not only to <hi>Preſerve</hi> but <hi>Perfume</hi> it, and render it as <hi>Fragrant</hi> as you can; not alone to your ſelves, but to others, by reviving the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of whatever was Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in him. Vindicating him from all <hi>Calumnies</hi> and <hi>Falſe Accuſations;</hi> and even Stiffling, or allaying <hi>True ones</hi> as much as you can. And indeed you can no better provide for your own <hi>Honour,</hi> than by this tenderneſs for your Deceaſed <hi>Husbands</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. And to add to this, you muſt be careful not to do any thing below your ſelf, or that your Husbaed could he have foreſeen it, ſhould juſtly be aſhamed of. It was the Dying Charge of <hi>Aguſtus Caeſar</hi> to his Wife <hi>Livia,</hi> viz. <hi>Beha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thy ſelf well, and Remember our Marriage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet the Beſt and Laſt <hi>Tribute</hi> you can moſt ſuitably Pay to him, is in the Care of the <hi>Children</hi> he leaves behind him, <hi>Thoſe Living Images of himſelf;</hi> They claiming
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:36870:35"/>a Double Portion of your <hi>Love,</hi> one upon their Native Right, as yours, the other as a Bequeſt in Right, their Deceaſed Father: And indeed, ſince by this Mournful Separation, you are to Supply the part of both Parents, it is very neceſſary you ſhould put on the Affection of a Father and Mother;</p>
               <p>Firſt, in a Sedulous care of their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and then in the Frugal and Prudent Management of what is left them by their Father, or what is Legally or Reaſonably their Part of Portion; For if of the firſt you are not Cautious and Diligent, you will find the Grief and Remorſe of it when it cannot be Redreſſed. For being <hi>Grown up,</hi> they will follow the Habit of their Youth: Some out of Fondneſs, not to part with their Children, and others out of Neglect, or too Frugal Sparing, that they may have great portions, have been Fatally overſeen in this particular, denying them the advantage of an <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nteel Breeding,</hi> to Swell their Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> but ſo contracted and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed their Minds, that they know not now to diſpoſe the Fortune to any real Benefit of themſelves: Sometimes, as I have ſaid, this defect proceeds from <hi>Femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:36870:35"/>Fondneſs, they know not how to part with them out of their Sight, though for their more immediate advantage, the Souls of ſuch Mothers being <hi>Bound up in their Children,</hi> as that of <hi>Jacobs</hi> in <hi>Benjamin.</hi> In this caſe, the Sons at leaſt, by being Confined at Home, are ſo <hi>Blown up</hi> and <hi>Corrupted,</hi> with the Flattery of <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Tenants,</hi> &amp;c, who think theſe the beſt expedients to ſecure their own Stations, that as if their Eſtates were the <hi>Confines</hi> of the World, they fancy to ſee nothing beyond them: So that when at laſt ſuch, an <hi>Heir</hi> breaks looſe from his Mothers Arms, he expects ſcarce to find his <hi>Equals,</hi> much leſs his <hi>Betters,</hi> he thinks he is ſtill to receive the ſame Fawning Adorations, and will ſcarce be undeceived but at the price of many Affronts, nay, perhaps, he may Buy his Experience with the loſs of his Life, drawing on Quarrels by his ill Manners, wherein he finally Periſhes; and this is no Impoſſible Suppſition, many unhappy <hi>Mothers</hi> have found to their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable Affliction; which Deplorable <hi>Misfortune,</hi> a Liberal <hi>Education</hi> might have prevented.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to be Frugal in managing what is your Childrens due, is very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:36870:36"/>and muſt by no means be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected: But in doing it you muſt not Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice them the other way, nor indeed, Incroach upon any thing that is theirs, to advance your ſelf in a Second Marriage, or to maintain your own State and <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure,</hi> for this not only Cancels your pretended Love to your Deceaſed <hi>Husband,</hi> in violating his Will, and the Truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in you, but a manifeſt Defrauding of your own Children, which is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Injury of all others, for it envenoms the Crime, and adds Unnaturalneſs to Deceit: Beſides, 'tis a Prepoſterous ſort of guilt, <hi>Orphans,</hi> and <hi>Widows,</hi> are in <hi>Scripture,</hi> linked together, as Objects of <hi>Gods and Good Mens Pity:</hi> A <hi>Widow</hi> to injure her <hi>Orphans,</hi> is like that Uncouth Expreſſion <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.3. <hi>A Poor Man that Oppreſſeth the Poor, is like a Sweeping Rain, that Leaveth no Food.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider then, Seriouſly, in thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, that Injuſtice of any ſort, is a grievous Sin.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When it is Complicated with Treachery alſo.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That of all Truſts, thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by the Dead, have ever been Eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:36870:36"/>and the Violation of them account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a manner Sacriligious; and if any <hi>Widow</hi> can find any allay to theſe, by the two remaining circumſtances, <hi>That it is the Truſt of a Husband, and the Intereſt of a Child,</hi> I ſhall acknowledge her a very <hi>Subtle Caſuiſt;</hi> but I think it is beyond her Skill, by Rules Divine or Moral.</p>
               <p>Having only hitherto ſpoke of what you owe to your Deceaſed Husband, I now proceed to what of peculiar Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, relates to your ſelf. God who has placed you in this World, to purſue the Intereſts of a Better, directs all the ſignal Acts of his Providence to that end, and intends they ſhould be ſo Interpreted; That every great change, that occurs, is deſigned either to call you from a wrong way, or to quicken your pace in the right. And you may the more conjecture when God takes away the Mate of your Boſome, and reduces you to Solitarineſs, he ſounds you a Retreat from she <hi>Gayeties,</hi> and <hi>Lighter Jollytries</hi> of the World, that with your cloſer <hi>Mourning,</hi> you may put on a more retired Temper of Mind, a Stricter and Soberer Behaviour, not to be caſt off with your Vail, but to be the conſtant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dornment of your Widowhood,</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:36870:37"/>
               <p>As this State requires a great Sobriety, and Degrees of Piety, ſo likewiſe it brings with it many Advantages and Advances towards them. The Apoſtle tells us 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34. <hi>She who is Married, Caret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the things of the World, how She may Pleaſe her Husband;</hi> But in this State, that care is overpaſt, and Heavenly things, by the removal of this <hi>Screen,</hi> ſtand fairer to view. You may now decline <hi>Martha</hi>'s Care of Serving, and chooſe <hi>Mary</hi>'s better part.</p>
               <p>Shake off thoſe Cares that Cloggs the Souls with a Hurry of Incumbrances in <hi>Domeſtick</hi> affairs; and conſider of more Refined things, that bring true Happineſs with them, to Joy and Rejoyce the Mind. We find <hi>God</hi> himſelf retrenches the <hi>Wife's</hi> Power of Binding her own Soul, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. <hi>Her Vows were Inſignificant, without her Husbands Confirmation; but the Widow might Devote herſelf to what Degree ſhe Pleaſed.</hi> Your Piety in this State has no Reſtraint from any other inconſiſtent Obligation, but may Mount as high as it can. Thoſe Hours that were before your Husbands Right, ſeem now to be Devolved on God, who Promiſes, <hi>To be a Husband to the Widow, and a Father
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:36870:37"/>to the Fatherleſs;</hi> ſo he is the grand Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of your Time; you may now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the time, Spent in former Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments of your <hi>Husband,</hi> into <hi>Colloquies</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Entercourſes</hi> with your <hi>Maker:</hi> So that that Love which was humane, may by the changing of its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, acquire a Sublimity, being Exalted to that which is Divine; and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was Expended in <hi>Gayeties,</hi> and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, now not requiſite, may be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in Works of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Charity:</hi> That ſo his <hi>Corruption</hi> you have loſt, may help you to put on an <hi>Incorruption; and</hi> your Loſs of a Temporary Comfort, ſtate you in one that is Eternal: Whilſt your <hi>Loyalty, Duty</hi> and <hi>Conjugal Affection,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the <hi>External Work</hi> and <hi>happnieſs</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> the <hi>Ardour</hi> of <hi>Cherubims,</hi> and the <hi>Joy of Saints,</hi> in <hi>Endleſs Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And having thus ſhewed what relates to Education, and a proſpect of Happineſs here and hereafter, I now proceed to Treat of ſuch things as may be uſeful, tho' ſome what in a lower degree, and may be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to you in Houſhold Affaires.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:36870:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> I hyſical Waters, and Cordial Drinks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to a Healthful Conſtitution, from the Choiceſt and Approved Receipts, of the moſt Eminent Perſons of this and former Ages: With their Proper Virtus how they ought to be taken, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers they are Good in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Apoplectick Water.</head>
                  <p>TAke four pound of Black-Cherries, bruiſe, and take away the Stones, add of the roots of Valerian and Fartſhorn ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, each three ounces, Roſemary, Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Sage, each a handful, Cloves and Mace beaten fine, each an ounce, Saffron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> drams, flowers of the Lilly of the Valley, a handful; bruiſe theſe and mix them well together, and diſtil'd, drink a quarter of an ounce faſting, in any convenient liquor, as warm Ale, Thea, Coffee, Wine, &amp;c. and it will help the Apoplexie, Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie, or any deſtempers proceeding from the Affliction of the Brain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Aqua Mirabilis, to make.</head>
                  <p>Take an ounce of the beſt Cinamon;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:36870:38"/>Nutmeg and Citron peel, each ſix drams, Gallingal, Cubebs, Cloves and Mace, each two drams, bruiſe them groſly, and infuſe them in a gallon of White-wine, and a quart of ſpirit of Wine, and ſo diſtil them: this taken half an ounce et a time, fortifies the Heart, reſiſts contagious Airs, Plague or Peſtilence, Feaver, or any vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Infections.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Elixir Salutis.</head>
                  <p>Lake four ounces of Senna, Elicampain roots and Guaicum two ounces, Anniſeeds, Carraway, and Coriander ſeeds, each the like quantity, Raiſins of the Sun ſtoned, half a pound, Liquorice ſliced, two ounces, Rheuburb thinly ſliced half an ounce, bruiſe and infuſe them in Brandy or a ſpirit drawn from Fruit, Malt, and Moloſſes, five or ſix days, then draw off the liquid part, and put it up in bottles cloſely Corked. This is excellent in the Chollick, or other pains in the Belly, for cleanſing the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and cauſing a good digeſtion, helps in all cold diſeaſes, and brings away the Gravil in the Kidneys or Bladder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Antinepretick Water.</head>
                  <p>Take of clarefied Honey, half a pound, Venice Turpentine, two ounces, Nepretick wood, and Reſt-harrow roots, of each, an
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:36870:39"/>ounce and a half, Maſtick, Galingal, Cloves Cinamon, Cubebs, Mace, of each half a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ounce, wood of Aloes, an ounce, bruiſe them groſly, and let them infuſe in two quarts of rectified Spirits, and ſo diſtill them. this is excellent good againſt the Stone or Gravel, eaſes pains of the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and all other pains of the Bowels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Elixir Proprietatis.</head>
                  <p>Take Alexandrian, Myrrh, Aloes, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotrine and Saffron, of each two ounces, bruiſe them very fine, put them into a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of White-wine, and a quart of rectified Spirits, let them infuſe eight days, then diſtill them in a moderately heated Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hath. and ſo preſerve the Spirit, mixing amongſt, when taken, ſome of the volatile ſpirit of Hartſhorn, <hi>viz.</hi> ſix drops to a quarter of an ounce. This purifies the Blood, and is exceeding good againſt the Sourvey, and all Diſtempers proceeding from corrupt humour; if it prove too hot, you may take it in Wine, or other palata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Liquors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Butler<hi>'s</hi> Ale.</head>
                  <p>Take Sarſaparilla two ounces, Polypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Oak and Sena, each four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Licoris two ounces, Carriway ſeeks, and Anniſeed, each an ounce, Agrimony,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:36870:39"/>and Maiden-hair, of each a pugil, or little handful, Scurvy-graſs leaves and ſtalks, a quarter of a peck, bruiſe them groſly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put them into a thin Canvas bag, into ſix gallons of New Ale, and at three days end, draw it off and fine it in Bottle. This purges the Urin, and gentle breathing Sweats, it expels Scorbutick hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and helps much in the Dropſie, and all watery diſeaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Purl-Royal.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of Coriander ſeeds, a handful of ſtript Roman Wormwood, an ounce of Senna, a little handful of Balm, an ounce of Horſe-Raddiſh-root, thinly ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, bruiſe theſe, and infuſe them in two gallons of White-wine, or Rheniſh-wine, ſix days, take away the liquid part, drink a ſmall glaſs full in as much other Wine. It fortifies the Heart, cleanſes the Stomach, and very much helpeth Digeſtion. Theſe ingredients may likewiſe be infuſed in Ale, or any other Liquor; in Ale it is called, <hi>Common Garden-Purl, a liquor very much eſteemed in</hi> London.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Spirit of Scurvey-Graſs.</head>
                  <p>Take the bark of the root of an Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, the root of Fraxinel, Capers, and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marisk, each an ounce, Oak Polypode, two
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:36870:40"/>ounces, wild Radiſh 3 ounces, Scurvygraſs-leaves, one pound, Sorrel, Water-creſſes, Brook-lime, and spleenwort, three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls each, Bayberries, and Berries of Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, of each half an ounce, a handful of the tops of the leſſer Centaury, the ſeeds of Muſtard, Citron, Cardus, each half an ounce, Cinamon, Cloves, Ginger, and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, each three drams, bruiſe theſe, and digeſt them in a warm Sand-bath, in a gallon of Rheniſh-wine, and three pints of true Brandy, three days, then diſtill them in an Alimbeck. Twenty drops in any Liquor is a ſufficient doſe, in caſe of the Scurvey, ſhortneſs of Breath, pricking Pains, foulneſs of the Lungs, Yellowneſs of the Teeth, eaſing pains of the Belly, killing Worms in Children; and for it's rare Virtues, is called, <hi>The Golden Spirit of Scurvey-Graſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Pligue Water.</head>
                  <p>Take Balm, Mint, Rhue, Cardus, and the green husks of Walnuts, or Walnut-leaves, of each a good handful, bruiſe them and infuſe them 24 hours in a gallon of Canary, add bruiſed Mace and Cinamon, each half an ounce, diſtill them, and drink an ounce of the Water faſting. It reſiſts all Peſtilential Airs, Infectious or Nauſeous
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:36870:40"/>Vapours, that offend Nature, is good in Surfeits, Pains of the Head, or Aſcending Vapours, that occaſion Dizzineſs, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Surfeit-Water.</head>
                  <p>Cut off the bottoms of Poppy-flowers, infuſe two large handfuls in two quarts of Brandy, 24 hours, wring them out, and put in as many freſh ones, till the Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy has the Red Tincture of them, then ſlice in Nutmeg, Ginger and Cinamon, each a quarter of an ounce, preſs out the liquid part, drop in a few drops of Oyl of Cloves, and ſweeten it with Loaf Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; keep it cloſe ſtop'd, and take an ounce at a time; It's a great Healer of the Stomach, gives Reſt, cauſe Sweat; and Rarifies the whole Maſs of Blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebaugh.</head>
                  <p>Take three gallons of neat Brandy, or good rectified Spirit, Spaniſh juce of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quorice ſix ounces, Raiſins of the sun ſton'd, a quarter of a Pound, ſliced Dates, the Stones taken out, the like quantity, the tops of Thyme and Balm, each a little handful, the tops of Roſemary, and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary flowers, two ounces each, Mace Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Coriander-ſeed, and Anniſeed, groſly bruiſed, each half an ounce, ſcent
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:36870:41"/>it with Orange or Citron water, or the flowers or peels of either, let this Maſs infuſe 5 or 6 days, in a Glaſs or Earthen Veſſel, put in ſix ounces of white Sugar-candy, beaten in fine powder, then draw or pour off the liquid part, as fine as may be; and what remains will make a weaker ſort, by putting other spirits to it. This is a pleaſant Liquor, a great friend to the Lungs, preventing cold diſtillations, and bringing away Phlegm or Rheum; it removes obſtructions in the Liver, helps ſhortneſs of Breach, and ſweetens it; it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hears the Spirits, and taken faſting, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents the bad effects of evil Airs; about three ſpoonfuls at a time, is a ſufficient Doſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Stephen<hi>'s</hi> great Cordial Water.</head>
                  <p>Take a Gallon of Claret, Canary, or Rheniſh Wine, Gallingal, Grains of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, Cinnamon, Nutmegs, Ginger, Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, and ſweet Fennel-ſeeds, of each three drams, Mint, the leaves of Red Roſes, Sage, Pellitory of the Wall, the tops of Roſemary, Thyme, Wild Marjorum, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, and the tops of Lavender-cotton, ſhred the Herbs, and groſly bruiſe the Spices, infuſe them the ſpace of two days, and diſtil them in an Alimbeck
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:36870:41"/>This mainly reſiſts Infectious Airs, is an Antidote againſt the Plague, and very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious: And ounce of it taken juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the coming of a cold fit of an Ague, and if it appear too hot, you may palliate it with cooling Liquors, it eaſies mightily, likewiſe pains in the Bowels; and is good taken by thoſe that are apprehenſive or fearful of the Small pox, when they go abroad, in times when its rife.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Metheglin, White.</head>
                  <p>Take ſweet Marjorum, Violet &amp; Straw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry leaves, and flowers, the tops of Thyme, Roſemary, Burrage, and Agrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, of each a little handful, the ſeeds of Coriander, Carriway, and ſweet Fennel, each half an ounce, a quarter of an ounce of beaten Mace, boil them groſly bruiſed in eight gallons of Spring-water gently, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hour ſcumming &amp; ſtraining them, being ſtrained, put into the liquor as much fine Honey, as will make it bear an Egg, ſo that ſome part of it may appear above the liquid, boil it again as long as any ſcum will riſe, when it is cool, put it up into a Veſſel, with about a pint of Ale Yeaſt; let it work three days, then hang five days, a bag of Spice in it, draw it off, and bottle it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:36870:42"/>
                  <head>Mead.</head>
                  <p>Take Sweet-Briar, roſemary, and Thyme, Agrimony, Bettony, and Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bright, the tops of Scabious, each a pugil, or as much as may be lightly held between the Fore-finger and thumb, put them in Spring-water, and lay a Stone or ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy cover to ſink them, infuſe them 48 hours, then take them out and boil them in another water, till the water be colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with them, very high, let them ſtand off the fire a day and a night, to infuſe in a third water, then boil it up, and to every gallon of Water, put a pound of Honey, that is into the ſtrained liquor; and when it will bear an Egg, work it together till the Honey is well diſſolved, let it ſeeth 12 hours, and boil it up with the whites and ſtells of half a dozen Eggs beaten together, then beat up the whites of two or three Eggs, with half a pint of Ale Yeaſt, put up the Liquor into a Cask, let it work three days, then hang a bag of Spices in it, groſly bruiſed, ten days: so draw it off, and bottle it. It is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent cooling liquor in Feavours, and moſt hot Diſeaſes, as alſo is the former, it Tempers and Allays the Heat of the Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:36870:42"/>of Rheuburb, then boil them with a few Chamomil flowers, over a gentle fire, and drink off the liquid part very hot, repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Chollick.</head>
                  <p>Take the oyl of ſweet Almonds, three ounces, Pelletory Water and White-wine, each a quarter of a Pint, Anniſeeds, and Chamomll flowers, eatch two drams, let them ſimper an hour over a gentle fire, then pour out the liquid part, and drink it very hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For pains in the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Take Henbane ſeed, and Hyſop ſeed, beat them together ſmall, diſſolve Gum Arabick in a little Water, and ſo drop it on the beaten ſeeds, ſo that it may make them up into little Pellets, if the tooth be hollow, put one of theſe into it, and ſtop it cloſe with Lint, if not, place it to the root of the Tooth, between that and your Cheek.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For an Ague.</head>
                  <p>Take a handful of the tops of the herb Rue, bruiſe them groſly, boil them in a quart of White-wine, till a third part be conſumed, and when the Ague ſit is coming, drink.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:36870:43"/>
                  <head>Noiſe in the Head.</head>
                  <p>Take a Clove of Garlick, peel it, and prick three or four holes in the middle, dip it in Honey, and put it into your Ear, ſtop it with black Wool; and ſo continue, at times for a day or two, and the noiſe will ceaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For a Fellon.</head>
                  <p>Take flower of Malt, a handful, Sope about the bigneſs of a Walnut, boil them together in Beer, till it is as thick as Paſte, then ſpread a Plaiſter, and lay it to the part grieved; and by often changing it, will draw it to a head an break it, then lay on a Plaiſter of Diaculum, and it will heal it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Lasks to ſtay.</head>
                  <p>Take Burdock-roots, half a handful ſcrape them and waſh them clean, the ſeeth them in fair water, till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and bath your belly and the ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of your feet, with the Decoction, very warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the ſtinging of any Venemous thing.</head>
                  <p>Bruiſe ſweet Almonds, and Aſh-tree leaves, or for want of them the inner bark, make a poultis with a little Honey and the juce of Rue, and apply it.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:36870:43"/>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Bloodſhot Eyes, or Sore Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take Lapis Calaminaris, half an ounce, white Sugarcandy the like weight, White-wine one ounce, heat the ſtone almoſt red hot, in a clear fire, beat it very fine, then mingle it with the reſt, and ſtrain the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid part through a linnen cloth, put it into a Glaſs, and uſe it with a feather as you ſee occaſion. Note, the ſtone muſt be without red ſpots, white and clear, or it may prove hurtful.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For a Burn, or Scald.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of old Cheeſe, an ounce of Olive Oyl, an ounce of Honey, and half an ounce of Bole Armoniak, mix theſe together, till they may be ſpread like a Poltis, and apply it to the place; for want of ſome of theſe you may uſe Oyl, white Lead, and Snew water, beaten and tempered together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For Blaſting, or St. <hi>Anthony</hi>'s Fire.</head>
                  <p>Take a new laid Egg, roaſt it hard, then take the White from the Yolk, put it into a Mortar, with half its weight of Copperas, bruiſe them together with ſome Oyl of Roſes, and apply the Maſs to the place afflicted, and it will allay the Swelling, and take away the Heat, it is alſo good to prevent all Fluſhing in the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:36870:44"/>Face; and cauſe Redneſs to diſappear</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Small Pox to Prevent, its Scarring the Face, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of Hogs-Lard, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pint of Roſe-water, Tuttia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dram, Oyl of Roſemary half an ounce, the powder of an hares Liver, or Hares blood dryed, two drams, make theſe up into a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oyntment, over a gentle fire; and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Scabs are drying on the Face, anoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it with it pretty warm, and let the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fall off of themſelves, then anoint yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Face with Oyl of Roſes, beaten up wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a little White-wine; and no Scars, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Pits, or Disfigurement will appear.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Prevent Hair falling off, in the Small-Pox.</head>
                  <p>Take the inward Rhind of a Young Oak-tree, a good handful, beat it ſmall then take half a handful of tops of Balm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vervine, boil theſe in a gallon of fair ſpring water, till a third part or more be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſtrain out the liquid part with ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> preſſing, and waſh your head with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> when the Diſtemper declines, and is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off, twice a day, pretty warm; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it will not only faſten the roots of the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> but refreſh and revive it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:36870:44"/>
                  <head>Sore Mouth, or Throat.</head>
                  <p>Take Marſhmallow tops, boil them in Whitewine and Honey, diſſolve as much Alom as will make the Liquid part ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what rough in the mouth, then ſtrain out the thinneſt, and gargle your mouth and throat with it often, pretty warm, and the Soarneſs will ceaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To procure Sleep or Reſt.</head>
                  <p>Take half a handful of Water-Lillys, bruiſe them in three pints of Malmſey, and let them infuſe twelve hours, add a dram of Opium, as much Poppy-ſeed, and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice-ſeed well bruiſed, and then diſtil them, and take (going to bed, or when reſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired) of the diſtilled water, from half a dram to a dram, in any convenient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Weakneſs of the Sight.</head>
                  <p>Take Eye-bright, fine Sugar, and ſweet Fennel-ſeed, beat theſe together, and drink about two drams of it in a morning Faſting, in a glaſs of Wine, or Beer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Ague to Cure.</head>
                  <p>Boil a good handful of the tops of Rue, in a quart of White-Wine, till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and when you feel the cold fit coming, ſtrain it, and drink it as hot as may, walk about the room as faſt as you
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:36870:45"/>can, and being ſomewhat tired, get into a warm Bed; in twice or thrice thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Ague will decline and go off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Refreſh the Senſes, and Reſtore the Memory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take Balm, Bugloſs dry'd Roſes, and Frankincenſe, beaten into Powder, of all about ſix ounces, infuſe them in three Pints of White-wine, when they are well brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and when they have infuſed twenty four hours, put them in an Alimbeck, and of the diſtilled water, take a ſpoonful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning faſting; and faſt an hour after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Scurvey.</head>
                  <p>Take the juyce of Scurvygraſs, Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſſes, and Brooklime, each two ounces, let them ſettle, and poor of the clearer part, Reniſh-wine a quart, the roots of Elecampain, Horſe-Radiſh, and Flower-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luce, thinly ſliced, each half an ounce, two Nutmegs, well bruiſed, put theſe into a ſtone Veſſel, that may be ſtop'd very cloſe, and morning and night drink a quarter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a point of it pretty warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Expel Sadneſs, or Melancholly.</head>
                  <p>Take Rue, Cranes-bill, a herb ſo called and Pulegium, of each a pugil, dry then in a Stove, or Oven, and beat them into
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:36870:45"/>powder, mix the powder with powder of Licoris, and Loaf-Sugar, ſinely ſcraped, make them up into <hi>Lozenges,</hi> with Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-water, and a little Saffron finely bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and eat about a quarter of an ounce every morning, faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Cure the Head-Ach.</head>
                  <p>In the firſt place waſh your Temples with fair water, then take Saffron Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incenſe, Vinegar, and Roſes, or Roſe-cake, beat them together, till they may be ſpread on a piece of Linnen Cloath, ſpinkle this over with a little Powder of Copporas, and lay it to the Forehead and Temples, Renewing it as you ſee occaſion; and it will take away the Heat, and eaſe the Pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Pluriſie.</head>
                  <p>Take the Diſtilled Water of <hi>Burnet,</hi> wherein Cinamon has been infuſed, an ounce at a time, three times a day, faſting each time, two hours after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Green-Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Extract of Mars, prepared with Musk, one ounce, Alloes Succotrine, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the juyce of Succory, ſix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rams, the Extract of Rheuburb, half an ounce, and of Saffron two drams, Oyl of Cinamon, ſix drops, mix them well, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:36870:46"/>make them up into ſmall Pills, each weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about a Scruple, take one of them faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in a morning, drink about a quarter of an hour after it, a glaſs of Wine, and walk about till you begin to be heated, or ſweat; and this repeated ſeveral mornings will, with the Bleſſing of God, anſwer your expectation in a wonderful manner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Stench Bleeding.</head>
                  <p>Take the tops of Young Nettles, and of Aſh leaves, dip a Linament in them and apply to the Noſtrils, Wound, or any other part that effuſes Blood, if the Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be Internal, mix ſome fine Sugar in it, and drink an ounce of it Blood-warm at a time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For a Prick under the Nail.</head>
                  <p>Make a Plaiſter of Turpentine, Bees-Wax, Mutton-ſuet, and the juce of Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leek, this alſo will draw out Splinters ſmall pieces of Iron or Thorns.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Melancholy to Suppreſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Clove-gilly-flowers, Couſlips, Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage-flowers, Conſerve of Roſes, each a ounce, Alkirms half an ounce, preſerve Citron, and Nutmeg, each an ounc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Beazar fifteen grains, Tincture of Saffro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> half a dram, make theſe up into an Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, with Syrup of Clove-gilly-flowers, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:36870:46"/>a drop or two of oyl of Cinamon; and when you find the Melancholly come upon you, which you may perceive by the Dulneſs or Lumpiſhneſs of your Spirits, take three drams of it in a Glaſs of Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadel, or old Malaga.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Megrim.</head>
                  <p>Take a handful of Ground-Ivy, waſh it clean, bruiſe it and boil it in a quart of Fine Ale, to the conſumption of a pint, drink it hot in a Morning Faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For a Feaver.</head>
                  <p>Make a Decoction of the tops of Rue, in Spring water, till it be very ſtrong, then ſtrain it, and add Wood-Sorrel, and Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en-hair, each a little handful, add more, ſome Slices of Liquorice, Nutmeg and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, ſtrain out the liquid part, and drop ten drops of the Spirit of Vitriol, into half a pint of it, and take half in pint at a time Morning Noon and Night; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to the Soles of the Feet, Tobacco leaves, beaten into a Moiſture, with a mixture of Blew Currans.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Falling Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take the Leaves and Berries of Oak Miſleto, with the top tender Branches, dry them in a Stove or Oven, beat them into Powder, and Sift it finely, and take
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:36870:47"/>about two drams in a Glaſs of of White-wine, of for thoſe of tenderyears, one dram: Do it Morning and Evening, eſpecially three days before and after the Full of the Moon, often repeating it; and it will prove very advantageous.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Diſeaſes in the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take the Water of Eye-bright, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pint, drop into it five or ſix drops of clarify'd Honey, the Powder of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Pearl and Coral, each a Scruple, ſhake them well, and often drop ſome of the water into your eyes: It helps In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamations, takes of Spots, and Celars the Sight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Evil.</head>
                  <p>Take <hi>Cuttlebone,</hi> uncalcined, ſcrape off the outſide, dry the white part, beat it into Powder, very fine; and often take half a dram into a ſpoonful of Aqua Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luae.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>Take the Roots of Gors, ſcrape them clean, and cut them into thin ſlices, the tops of Thime, Hyſop, Penny-Royal, and Netties, of each a handful, Carrawayſeeds, Elicampain-roots, each an ounce, bruiſe them and boyl them in fair water, till the liquid part is near conſumed, then ſtrain
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:36870:47"/>out what remains into two quarts of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh-wine, bottle it up cloſe; and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nine ſpoonfuls in the Morning faſting, two hours after dinner, and going to bed, uſe it often; and the watery humour will abate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To help Hearing.</head>
                  <p>Take the Chive in a Clove of Garlick, run a piece of fine Silk thorough it, that it may be eaſily pulled out upon occaſion, then cruſh it between your Fingers, put it in anointed over with the Oyl of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, when you go to Bed, and ſtop your Far with Cotten, or Black Wool; and in twice or thrice doing, your Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if not utterly loſt, will be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For a Conſumption: an Excellent Receipt.</head>
                  <p>Take the Herbs Lungwort, Liverwort, Rue, Hyſop, Sage, each a handful, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campain, and the roots of Sweet Flag, each half an ounce, Anniſeeds, Carraway-ſeed, Sweet Fennel ſeeds, each the like quantity, Burrage, and Bugloſs-flowers, each two drams, infuſe them 24 hours in two quarts of Old Maliga, or good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, being well bruiſed, add then Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Cardus-water, each two ounces,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:36870:48"/>then diſtill them, and drink about two ounces at a time, eſpecially faſting. This is a great Strengthner of the Lungs, and attenuates the vicious humours from the Liver, expels VVind out of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and Bowels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Biles to Break and Cure.</head>
                  <p>Roaſt white Lylly-roots in ſoft Embers, bruiſe Figs with Fennel-ſeed, and Hemp-ſeed, each a quarter of an ounce, beat them together, and boil them in new Milk till they thicken, then add 2 ounces of Hogs-Lard, and lay it to the Grieved part.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII. <hi>Cookery:</hi>
                  </hi> Or, the Art of Dreſſing <hi>Fiſh, Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Fowl,</hi> after the Neweſt and Exacteſt way, with their Proper Sawces, Garniſhes, and manner of Serving up.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Strengthning Jelly of Fleſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke a well Fleſh'd Cock, and a Knuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle of Mutton, or the Sinews and Knuckle of Veal, and little Mutton,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:36870:48"/>Raiſins of the Sun ſtoned, half a pound, bruiſe theſe to pieces in three Gallons of VVater, then ſtamp the Meat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and boil it with the Liquid part up to a pritty thickneſs, then run it through a ſtrainer, with hard preſſing, and when it has ſtood all night, skim off the top, and ſeaſon the reſt with Sugar and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Nutmeg ſliced with ſome ſmall pieces of Cinamon and a blade or two of Mace, boil it up and ſtrain it again; and this being eaten in a Morning faſting, is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully Strengthning and Reſtoring to Nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Lobſter Stewed.</head>
                  <p>Take Butter, Salt and Red VVine Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, and put into your Stew-Pan, then grate a little Nutmeg, ſo cut the Fleſh of the Tail and Claws of the Lobſter in ſquare thick bits, the faſhion of Dice, put them into the Stew ſauce, covering it with a Diſh, then when it begins to grow dry, run it over with Butter, Garniſh'd with ſlices of Lemon, and ſo ſerve it up with grated Manchet, it being ſeaſoned with Grape Verjuce or VVhite-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To haſh a Lobſter.</head>
                  <p>Clear him of the Shell as ſoon as boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cut the meat in fine thin ſlices,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:36870:49"/>put it into a Earthen Veſſel, near cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Claret, then put a ſprinkling of Salt, a good piece of Sweet Butter, and the juce of a Lemon, being ſtewed, put it upon Sippets, and run it over with Butter, and Garniſh the Diſh with ſlices of Orange; and ſo Serve it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Collar Beef,</head>
                  <p>Take Sinews out of the Flank piece, as alſo the moſt Skinny part, and ſome of the Fat, then cover it with Water and Salt, and ſteep it twenty four hours: So hand it a draining in a Linnen-Cloth, in the Air, ſhred the tops of Mint, Sage, Savoury, Marjorum, and Thime, beat a quarter of an ounce of Mace, half a quarter of an ounce of Cloves, a ſlice or two of ginger, and half an ounce of Pepper, mix theſe with Salt, and rub over the Beef, rowling it up hard, and baking it in a Soaking Oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake a Wild Cooſe, or Mallard,</head>
                  <p>Par-boil either thoſe, then break the Breaſt and flat it down, then ſeaſon them with Pepper, Nutmeg and Salt, within and without, if they be not very Fat of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Lard them, and put them into a deep Coffin, with Butter above and beneath; and when they are well Soak'd poor melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:36870:49"/>Butter, with a Funnel, into the vent you have left open on the top of the Lid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Souce a Pig.</head>
                  <p>Scald a large Pig, and having take off the Head, ſlit it in the middle, take out the Bones, and waſh it in warm water, then with ſtrewing of Salt, grated Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and beaten Mace, rowl it up as you do Brawn, into a Collar; hinding it round with Baſs cordage, then boyl it in ſpring-water, till it be tender, ſo being taken up, put it into cold water, wherein a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Salt or two has been diſſolved; and this will make the Skin very white, then take about two quarts of the water where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was boiled, as much White-wine Vinegar, a Race of Ginger ſliced, and two Nutmegs, ſo ordered, a quarter of an ounce of whole Pepper, and half a handful of Bay-leaves, ſeeth theſe well together, and being cold put the fleſh into it, and it will keep half a Year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Souce a Pike, Carp, Breem, Tenth, Trout, or Barbel,</head>
                  <p>Dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v either of theſe, but ſcrape not off the Scales, waſh the Roe and Liver, and ſlit them into long peices, then take two quarts of fair water, one of White-wine
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:36870:50"/>and a bundle of ſweet herbs, ſet them over a quick fire, and when they have boiled a little, put in the Fiſh, and pour in half a pint of Vinegar to hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them; being boyled, but not tender, take them up, and put into the Liquor whole Pepper, Ginger and Cloves, adding ſome ſalt, and being well boiled, pour it hot to your Fiſh, and cover them with Mint, Balm, Fennel, or ſuch like ſweet herbs; and when you ſerve them up, ſhred the herbs, ſprinkle a little Ginger on them; and pour Vinegar to them in Sawcers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Woodcock, Larks, Blackbirds, or Sparrows, to Bake, the beſt way.</head>
                  <p>Truſs them, Parboil them, and ſo ſeaſon them with Pepper, Salt and Ginger, and if you pleaſe, Lard them, then put them into a Coffin covered with Butter, mixed with a few ſweet Herbs, all ſhred and beaten in a Mortar; and being Baked enough, draw them and pour in other Butter, beaten with the Yolk or two of an Egg.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Red Deer to make: Or make Beef look like it.</head>
                  <p>Parboyl it, and Preſs it, and let it ly all night in Red Vvine, and a ſmall quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:36870:50"/>of Vinegar, then Lard it thick, and ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt, Cloves, Mate and Nutmeg, or if you will, a little Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger finely beaten, then lay it into your Pye or Paſty, with ſtore of Butter; let it be well ſoak'd, and when you draw it out of the Oven, pour in at the Vent, Butter, Nutmeg, Sugar and a little Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, beaten together; and ſo put it into the Oven again half an hour, and thus you may make Tender Beef paſs for Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Neats Tongues to Haſh.</head>
                  <p>Boyl and Blanch them, and ſlice them in ſlices, then put the pieces into a Pipkin, with Raiſins of the Sun, large Mace, three or four Blades, blanched almonds, Claret, boyl them altogether, and add a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſweet Butter, ſome Verjuce and a little Sugar, ſtrain a Ladle or two of the Liquor, and beat it up with the Yolk of two or three Eggs, place it on carved Sip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, and Garniſh with ſlices of Lemons Parſley, and pickled Barberries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Collar Eles.</head>
                  <p>Take the largeſt ſilver Eles; cut then open with the Skin on; take out the bones, then beat ſome ſweet Herbs, with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and a little Ginger, and ſtrew them
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:36870:51"/>on the inſide of the Eels, then rowl them up three in a breadth, &amp; bind them up with Baſs flag, boyl them in three parts Water, and one Wite-wine; and as the boyl gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, put in ſome ſlices of Nutmeg, Ginger, and whole Pepper, being ſomewhat tender, cool them in water, then drain that from them, and put in the Liquor they were boyl'd in, with a little White-wine Vinegar: Serve it up, garniſhed with Bay-leaves and ſlices of Oranges: and for Sauce Oyl and Muſtard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Giblets to Dreſs with Herbs, and Roots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Parboyl them and put them into a quart of Claret in a Pipkin, or Earthen veſſel, add an ounce of Sugar, ſome Pickled Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, and Spinage, a fagot of ſweet herbs and ſuch roots as you think convenient, ſliced, then take ſtrong Broath, Verjuice, and the Yolks of two or three new laid Eggs, ſtrain them and put them into the Pipkin, and let them ſtew together: So Serve them on Sippets, Garniſhed with Flowers or Greens.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Chickens and White Broath.</head>
                  <p>Truſs and Parboyl your Chickens, till they become very White, then ſhred ſweet
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:36870:51"/>Herbs to them, with ſome blades of Mace, and peices of Cinamon, ſhred a little Parſly, then ſtrain the Yolks of four or five Eggs, with ſome Virjuce, which you muſt put in when they are ready to be taken up, place them on carved Sippets, and Garniſh with Parſly, Hyſop, and ſliced Lemons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Haſh Deer, Sheep or Calves Tongues.</head>
                  <p>Boyl either of theſe prety well, then Blanch them, draw them with ſmall ſprigs of Roſemary, then put then on a Spit, till they are half Roaſted, then ſlice them and put them into a Pipkin, or another Earthen Veſſel, that will endure the fire, with as much Claret, as will cover them, put in after they have boyled a while, ſome Cinamon, Ginger, and ſliced Lemon, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Mace, and ſome Sugar, boyl theſe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and Diſh them upon Fryed Toaſts, Garniſh with ſlices of Lemon, and grated Manchet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Boyl a Wild Duck or Mallard.</head>
                  <p>Truſs and Parboyl it, then half roaſt it, carve it, and let out the Gravey, which you muſt ſave, then take Onions, Parſly, Ginger, and Pepper, boyl them together, then mix the Gravy with them,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:36870:52"/>being chopped, or bruiſed very ſmall then add a few Currans and ſome grated White-Bread, make theſe thin with Broth, and ſo on Sippits ſerve it up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt run over with Claret and Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey beat up together; and this is a very good way to boyl a Tame Duck, Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, or Moor-Hen, to be received very acceptably.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Pigeons or any ſmall Fowl to Boyl.</head>
                  <p>Parboyl them with beaten Parſley and Butter in their Bellies, then put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Boyler with ſtrong Broth, add a blade of Mace, and ſome groſs Pepper, with half a pint of white-wine, grate a little bread into the broth to whitten the Fowl; and ſo ſerve them up with the Gravy and a diſſolved Anchovy, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with Parſly and Violets, or their leaves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Sauſages to Boyl.</head>
                  <p>Put a pint of Claret to a quart of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put in ſome ſweet herbs finely ſhred, a blade or two of Mace, and ſome Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, let them boyl about a quarter of an hour, then ſerve them up with beaten Ginger, Cinamon or Muſtard and Sugar, in Sawcers.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:36870:52"/>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Stew Trouts, Carp, Tench, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Draw them and ſcrape them well, waſh them in White-wine, then ſmeer them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with a piece of Sweet Butter, and lay them orderly in a Stew-pan, putting in as much water as will cover them above an inch, with a little Salt, a bundle of ſweet herbs, and ſome blades of Mace, take them up, and make your Sawce of beaten Butter, Claret, yolks of Eggs, and Sugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Lamb to make like Veniſon.</head>
                  <p>Bone it, and take the ſide or quarter, and dip it in its Blood, ſprinkle it over with Salt, Cinamon and Pepper, rowl it up, and parboyl it, adding ſome Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to the Water you boyl it in, a ſprig or two of Hyſop and Thyme, let it ſtand ſix hours in the water when it is off the Fire, put it into a coffin, and pour to it when half Baked, Claret and Melted Butter, with ſome Cloves Mace and dryed Roſemary, finely beaten.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Shoulder of Mutton with Oyſters.</head>
                  <p>Stuff your Mutton with ſtrong Oyſters, of a moderate ſize, and ſweet herbs, roaſt it before a pretty quick Fire, baſting it with Butter, and ſaving the Gravy which falls from it, ſeparate from the Fat, make
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:36870:53"/>it into a Sauce, with Claret, Pepper, and grated Nutmeg, then lay the Oyſters that you pull out about the Mutton, Garniſh it with Parſly, and ſlices of Lemon; and ſo ſerve it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Chikin in Whito-Broath.</head>
                  <p>Put three points of Strong Broath, to a quart of good white-wine, then put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Pipkin or ſome othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Earthen Veſſel, as many Chickens as it will Conveniently boyl, and when it begins to ſimmer ſlice ſome Dates, and put into it, with three or four blades of Mace, and half a pound of Beef Marrow, ſhred ſome white Endive ſmall, and ſtrew in a few ſweet herbs; let them ſtew over a moderate fire, and the Broath being a little ſtrong, ſtrain in the yolk of two or three Eggs, ſtir them about till enough, then take them up, Diſh it with Marrow, Dates, large Mace, the Broth, and Sippets; Garniſh with pickled Grapes, and Barbaries, or for want of them, Parſly, and red Beats.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make China Broth.</head>
                  <p>Take an ounce of China-root, thinly ſliced, ſteep it twelve hours, in two quarts of fair water, on moderate Embers, and then put a pritty big Cock-chicken into it, put Maiden hair, and Wood-ſorrel, beaten
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:36870:53"/>with Raiſins, Currans, and Dates into the Belly, tying up the vent, add a handful of French Barley well bruiſed, and when the chicken is boyled almoſt to a Jelly, ſtrain out the Broth, if there wants water, you may add more in the boyling. This is an excellent ſtrengthener reſtorer of Nature, when decay'd or waſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Hare Haſhed.</head>
                  <p>Cut it out in quarters, chine it, and lay it in Clarret, mixed with three parts of water, and parboyl it, then ſlice the fleſh in thin pieces, and lay it n your ſtew pan, let this be off the Body, but the legs wings, and head keep whole, almoſt cover it with ſome of the liquor it was boyled in, add ſome Butter, ſliced Nutmeg, the juce of Lemon, and a little beaten Ginger, ſerve it upon Sippets, Garniſh it with Lemon, and ſliced Onion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Carp to Roaſt.</head>
                  <p>Beat Blanched Almonds into a paſt, with Cream, grated Bread, ſweet Herbs, finely ſhred, Currans, Salt, a little beaten Nutmeg, and Ginger, draw you Carp at the Gills, and put in the Pudding at the ſame place, faſtening it to the Spit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out running it into it, do it by tying on,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:36870:54"/>prick the belly to let out the Gravy, the ſauce it with the Gravy, powder of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, ſweet Butter and the juce of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranges, beat up with a little Claret and ſweet Herbs, ſhred ſmall and boyled ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Garniſh with ſlices of Lemon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Stew a Carp.</head>
                  <p>Scrape off the Scale, make it clean with in and without ſave the Blood, and mingle it with a pint of Claret, lay i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in a ſtew-pan, with as much water and white-wine as will cover it, ſprinkle it over with beaten Cloves, Ginger, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg and ſweet Herbs, quarter in a large Onion, put in about half a pound of Butter, and when it boyls up, put in the Blood and Claret; and when it is enough ſerve it up, Garniſhing with ſlices of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranges and Greens. And in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you may Dreſs a <hi>Breem, Barble, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Trout, Pike,</hi> or any not over large Fiſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Cods Head to Dreſs.</head>
                  <p>When it is fair and largly cut, boyl it with all its appurtenances, in Spring or Conduit-water, with a ſeaſoning of Salt, and about a pint of VVhite-wine Vinegar, fill the mouth with ſtewing Oyſters, and cloſe it with a ſtring, put in a faggot of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:36870:54"/>ſweet Herbs, and a quartered Onyon; when it is boyled, take it up carefully, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et it to draining, take Oyſter-pickle, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw liquor of Oyſters, the Boyled Onyon, three or four Anchovies, a quarter of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>int of VVhite-wine, ſhred into theſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aggot of ſweet herbs, clean ſtript from their ſtalks, beat them up with a pound of ſweet butter, lay the Oyſters in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, about and upon the Fiſh pour on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auce, Garniſh with Lemon and red Beets. Thus you may dreſs young <hi>Codlins</hi> or large <hi>Whitings,</hi> adding to the ſtewed Oyſters, ſome Shrimps, or Prawns, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Roaſt a Salmon.</head>
                  <p>Take it either whole or a Jole, or Rand, ſeaſon it with Salt Ginger and grated Nutmeg, ſtick it with whole cloves Bay-leaves and Roſemary-tops, ſpit and baſt it with Butter, ſprinkle a little with the juce of a Lemon, and what drops from it, beat up with Butter, and the juce of Orange, for Sauce; as alſo the Yolks of two or three Eggs: laſtly add Verjuce, powder of Cinamon, and Claret; Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing with Fennel, and ſlices of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:36870:55"/>
                  <head>To Fry Salmon.</head>
                  <p>Take the Chine, or Rand, cut in fine th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> peices, put it into freſh Butter, when mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately hot in your Pan, keep it turning till it grows ſomewhat Criſp, Sauce it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſweet Butter, Nutmeg, and Claret, we beaten up with the juce of an Orange, and pickled Oyſter Liquor; Garniſh with fry'd Bay-leaves, and Lemon peel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Stew a Tnrbut.</head>
                  <p>Cut it in fine large peices, fry it a little in freſh Butter, then drain it well, take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out and put it into your ſtew-pan, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> beaten Nutmeg, Claret, the Juce of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range, add a ſufficiency of ſweet butte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and being ſtewed, put more melted butte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Orange Juice: Garniſhing it, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſlices of Orange, and ſerve it up.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:36870:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Terms and Art of <hi>Carving,</hi> of Fowl, Fiſh, Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Proper Sauces, and Garniſhings, more Particularly, than <hi>Sweetracats,</hi> and other Rarities.</head>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Lift a Swan.</head>
                  <p>LAy it on the Back, and ſlit it down in the middle of the breaſt, and divide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the Neck to the Rump, without breaking or tearing it, place the two halves, the ſlit ſide downard, ſtrew ſome Salt and Cinamon about it, and ſerve up Chaldron Sauce, in Saucers, Garniſhing with water-Lillys, water-Creſſes, or any ſuitable flowers, or greens, growing in or by the water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Cut up a Turkey, or Buſtard.</head>
                  <p>The Legs being raiſed up very fair, open the joynt with the point of your Knife, but take them not off, proceed to lace the breaſt down on both ſides, open the breaſt pinion, but not take it off, ſo raiſe the <hi>Merry-Thought,</hi> between the breaſt-bone and the top of it; and on both
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:36870:56"/>ſides the breaſt-bone, lace the fleſh that is called the brawn, and turn it outward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on both ſides, but neither break it, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> take it off. Then take off the VVing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pinions at the joynts next the body, and place on each ſide the pinion, where the brawn was turned out, but cut off the ſharp end of it, and ſit the place with the middle piece. Make your ſauce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gravey, Pepper, Red wine, a ſlice or tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Nutmeg, or the yolks of Eggs beate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> up with Red wine Butter and Vinegar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Garniſh wiih Fennel, Parſly and ſlice of Lemon. This way you may carve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a <hi>Pheaſant</hi> or <hi>Capon,</hi> but of the latter, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not off the Pinions, but in the place where you put them in the <hi>Turkey,</hi> &amp;c. place the Gizzard; Sawce theſe with Gravy and Anchovy Sauce; and Garniſh with ſlices of Orange and Greens.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>A Horn to Diſmember.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Legs, disjointing them with the point of your Knife, lace it down the breaſt, and raiſe up the fleſh take it away with the pinion, and place the head in the breaſt, and place the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions on the contrary ſide of the carcaſs, and on the other ſide the Legs, that the ends of the bones may meet croſs over
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:36870:56"/>it, and the wings over the top: Sauce it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith the juce of Lemon, Sugar, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on and Claret, a peice or two of Onyon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oiled in fair water with the Neck, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>izzard added to them; and Garniſh with any pleaſant Flowers or Greens and Lemon peel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>A Mallard to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbrace.</head>
                  <p>In doing this raiſe up the pinion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g, but take neither of them off, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at the <hi>Merry-Thought,</hi> and ſo lace it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>own on either ſide on the breaſt bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Knife too and frow; Sauce it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith the boyling of the Neck, Gizzard, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iver, Pepper, and Claret, Garniſh with grated Bread, Salt and Slices of Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es; and ſo order a Duck if roaſted, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyled, with Sippits Sugar and juce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Wing a Partridge.</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the VVings and Legs, take off the reſt of the Fleſh, Mince it and Sauce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t with Claret, beaten Ginger, Salt, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle grated Nutmeg, and the gravy that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omes from it; Garniſh with Parſly, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lets or Marygold flowers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njoyn a Bittern, or Wing a Quail.</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the Legs and VVings and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:36870:57"/>Sauce them with Salt, and the Grave without Garniſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To diſplay a Crane.</head>
                  <p>Take off the Wings by the body-point unfold the Legs, then take up the Legs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wings, Sauce them with powder of Ging<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Vinegar, Salt and Muſtard well beaten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gether; Garniſh with Manchets, pickle Lettice-ſtalks, or Purſlain-ſtalks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To untach a Curlew</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the Legs and wings, ſprinkle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with Salt, Sauce it with grated white-bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Claret and grated Nutmeg, Garniſh it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſlices of Lemon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Mince a Plover of any Kind.</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the legs and wings, ſprinkle it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Salt, Sauce it with the juce of Lemon, Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, white-wine, and a Shalot boyled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Thigh a Woodcock</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the legs, dot his Brains, ſprink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him with Salt, and powder of Ginger, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> him with Anchovie Sauce, and gravy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for want of theſe with Butter and Vinega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in which, ſtript Thime, is ſhred ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſmall, being firſt boyled; Garniſh wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lemon-peel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Cut up a Snite.</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the legs, wings, and Breaſtpei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:36870:57"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>divde the remainder in four parts, Sauce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with beaten Parſley, Butter, Vinegar, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e gravy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Sauce a Cock, Capon or Pullet.</head>
                  <p>Take off the legs and wings, place them in either ſide, then raiſe the Merry thought, after that the ſide pieces down the Breaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen take off the belly-piece, ſo turn up the Carcaſs, cut the back aſunder, and divide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in four pieces, placing them between the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ings and the legs: Sauce them either with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gg Sauce, or the Neck and Gizzard, boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d with pepper and water with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y; Garniſh with ſlices of Lemon and Parſly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Allay a Pheſant.</head>
                  <p>Raiſe the legs and wings, as of the former, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rinkle Salt round it, and Sauce it with Chichup, Claret, Sugar, and thin ſlices of Nutmeg; garniſh with bay-leaves and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Orange, or Lemon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Rear a Gooſe.</head>
                  <p>Take off the legs, cut off the belly-peice, cloſe to the lower end of the breaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace her down on both ſides the breaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tliumbs-breadth, from the breaſt-bone-ridge, take off the pinions on each ſide, and the fleſh which is laced, raiſe quite from the bone, cut up the <hi>Merry thought;</hi>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:36870:58"/>take off the ſlice on the top of the brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the carcaſs, and cut it in halv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long ways, lay the rump in the fore-e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Merry-Thought,</hi> and before it the bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> piece, place theſe in decent order, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſauce it with Muſtard and Sugar, in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Apple-ſauce or Gravy, Pepper a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Shallot as you like beſt; and no Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To Thigh a Pigeon.</head>
                  <p>Take off the Legs and Wings, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the carcaſs in four parts, and lay the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> decently in order, as if it was ſtill whole.</p>
                  <p>And thus you may do with <hi>Thruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Blackbird, Teal, Widgeon, Wheat-Ears, Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, Ducklins, Turkey-Pouts, Dottrel, Puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins,</hi> and all others of the like bigneſs; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for all ſmaller Birds, as <hi>Larks, Sparron, Finches Wood-peckers, &amp;c.</hi> only cut them in four quarters, ſauce them with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Vinegar the juce of a Lemon, and Parſley boyled, and finely ſhred; and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this method you have the general and particular terms of Carving, and may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it accordingly; and in the cutting up and carving other Fowl not here mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe being the principal, in uſe at Feaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of all ſizes.</p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:36870:58"/>
                  <p>For <hi>Fiſh</hi> there is no great difficulty in cutting it up, becauſe it is generally order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when brought to the Table, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall only note, that the beſt piece is that next the Head, the next the Middle-peice, and the Tail by many not much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of: If a Fiſh be large turn it on the belly, divide it down the back, and laying the ſides open, divide them into three parts; yet for your better inſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſomething you may meet withal one time or other, and think difficult I ſhall not ſo ſilently paſs over this part of Carving.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>The madner of Carving, Fiſh, with their Proper Sauce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Hack <hi>Herring,</hi> and lay it whole on a Trencher, or Plate, the Back-bone and Roe, being taken out of all ſalt Fiſh, ſalt <hi>Salmon Green Fiſh</hi> or <hi>Conger,</hi> pair away the Skin; <hi>Mackerel Marling,</hi> and <hi>Stock-fiſh,</hi> lay it flakes. And <hi>Pike</hi> muſt be laid on the belly on a plate, the back opened, the bone taken out, and Sauced with Clarret, Nutmeg and Ginger, Butter and the juice of a Lemon. A ſalt <hi>Lamprey</hi> muſt be Skinned, and cut in Seven or eight peices: As for <hi>Pince</hi> Boyled, pour out the water from them, croſs them with your knife,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:36870:59"/>Sauce them with wine, ſalt butter and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, and garniſh with green things. And ſo you may order <hi>Dace, Gug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ons, Roach Mullet, Chiven, Pearch, Sole, Whiting, Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> and <hi>Godleng;</hi> only raiſe either of theſe by the back, clean the belly, and take ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the back-bone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bream Carp</hi> or <hi>Trout,</hi> muſt be boned, and ſo laid whole together again. But as for <hi>Conger, Salmon, Sturgeon, Turbut, Toornback,</hi> cut them up and lay them in order, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the dreſſing of Fiſh, is in many particular more plainly directed.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sauces</hi> for <hi>Fiſh</hi> are theſe, Viz. <hi>Muſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> for <hi>Salt Conger, Oyl Vinegar</hi> and <hi>Muſtard</hi> with <hi>Salmon, Herring,</hi> and <hi>Sparthings, Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Eel,</hi> and <hi>Ling, Verjuice,</hi> and <hi>Butter;</hi> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Roach, Dace, Bream, Mallet,</hi> and <hi>Flounders Gallenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> with Salt <hi>Lamprey,</hi> and <hi>Sturgeo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Crab,</hi> and <hi>Chiven,</hi> with <hi>Vinegar,</hi> beaten <hi>Cin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and <hi>Ginger;</hi> with all <hi>Green Fiſh, Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Sauce</hi> is proper: Though with Freſh <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> but,</hi> uſually <hi>Muſtard;</hi> and ſo of others to tedious here to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> be mentioned, but ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> better occur in other parts of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Work.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Butchers Meat</hi> it greatly concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> you, not as to the rules of <hi>Carving,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> that is ſo commonly ſeen, and eaſie to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:36870:59"/>performed, that I believe none can miſs it; only the Cutting up of a <hi>Coney</hi> or <hi>Hare,</hi> which is ſomething difficult, I have not yet ſpoken off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlace a Coney.</head>
                  <p>Lay it on the back, cut up the belly, then raiſe the wings, and ſides, take off the legs, and lay the four part of the body and chine together, and the belly pieces on each ſide: Sauce it with Butter Vinegar, the Liver ſhred ſmall, with boyled <hi>Parſley,</hi> and ſome powder of <hi>Ginger,</hi> Garniſh with <hi>Lemons, Salt,</hi> and of <hi>Ginger.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="carving_instructions">
                  <head>To break a Hare.</head>
                  <p>Lay her on her belly, cut her down the chine, then take off the ſhoulders, legs and belly pieces, lay them in order on the ſides of the Diſh, cut off the Tail-pieces, or Huntſmans piece; divide the chine and the hallow trunk, ſplit the Head, and lay it in the fore part of the Diſh. Sauce it with <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Pepper, Ginger, Clarret, Vinegar, Gallantine,</hi> and crums of White Bread; <hi>Garniſhing</hi> with thin ſlices of <hi>Red Beets</hi> and <hi>Red Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:36870:60"/>
               <head>Pickles for <hi>Sauces;</hi> and keeping <hi>Summer-Fruit,</hi> all the <hi>YEAR.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <head>Cucumbers to Pickle.</head>
                  <p>Take them of a ſmall ſize, or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently well choſe to your purpoſe, waſh them clean from duſt, and let them lay four hours in Salt and water cold, then boyl up good Rape Vinegar, or White-wine Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, with ſome Salt, Ginger, Dill, a little whole Pepper, and Coriander-ſeed, ſcum off the froth that ariſes, then put the cold water and ſalt, from the Cucumbers, and put the hot liquor to them into a cloſe Cask or Veſſel ſtopp'd, and they will not only be very green, but keep all the Year. Thus you may pickle French-beans, ſlices of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nip, Purſlain, Lettice, or Endive ſtalks, only theſe muſt be pretty well ſcalded in fair-water, before they are put into the Pickle, Do Broom-buds, as you do Cucumbers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <head>To Pickle Barberries.</head>
                  <p>Boyl water and ſalt, ſcum it well, and let it boyl till it will near bear an Egg,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:36870:60"/>marſt ſome Barberries into it, and Boyl them to colour it, and when it is cool, put it to your other Barberries. Thus you may Pickle Samphire, only adding a little Vinegar to the Brine: Alſo green Grapes, Plumbs, Cherries, Peaches, Quinces, young Apples, Green Apricocks, or the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <head>Muſhrooms.</head>
                  <p>Muſt be juſt Scalded in fair water, then put in cold White-wine Vinegar with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Mace Ginger and Coriander-ſeeds, cover them with Bay-leaves, and keep them cloſe ſcumming them and putting a little freſh Vinegar once a Month. This way you may keep them, at leaſt three quarters of a Year.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <head>Clove Gilly Flowers.</head>
                  <p>When you have infuſed them for Syrup and preſſed the Flowers hard, Boyl up vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Sugar gently, and ſcum it, put the flowers into it very hot, with ſome Blades of Mace, and bit or two of Cinamon: And thus you may pickle any ſort of Flowers. For Garniſh, Sallade, or Sauce, which at all times would not be had.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:36870:61"/>
                  <head>To keep Fruit for Tarts as they Grew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take large Stone-bottles, with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary fit Corks, well boyled, that they may ſwell cloſe when thurſt in, put them into an Oven, after you have clean waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, dry and evaporate the groſs air, then immediately fill them with unripe Gooſeberries, Damſons, hard, Cherries, Apricocks, or ſuch like fruits, uſed in Tarts, and at many times not to be had, ſtop them up cloſe, ſet them in a dry, but not a hot place, &amp; they'l keep their natural taſt and colour, all the Year; only they often happen to ſhrivel a little, which in haking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Plumps up again; and by this means the noted Paſtry-men have them at all Seaſons, which makes the Ignorant fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they have them brought from a far Country, in which at that time it is Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Grapes if not too pripe, may be ſo kept till <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="pickling_recipes">
                  <head>To Pickle Oyſters.</head>
                  <p>Boyl up water and Pepper, groſly bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſcum it well, and when it is ſtrong of the Pepper, put in ſome ſlices of Nutmeg, Ginger, a few Bay leaves and the liquor of the Oyſters, with a ſprinkling of Salt, ſtrain out the liquor when it taſts well of
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:36870:61"/>the ſpices, take ſtewing Oyſters, perboyl or ſcald them in fair water, ſo put them into the warm Pickle, and barrel and pot them up for your uſe, So you may Pickle Muſcles, Cockles, and any ſmall Shell-Fiſh, of the like Nature.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Art of <hi>Paſtery:</hi> Or, Direction for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pyes, Tarts Cuſtards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Cuſtards to make.</head>
                  <p>DRy the Paſt when you have formed it to your mind, till it grow ſtiff, then break about a dozen Eggs, beat them up to a thinneſs, and put them into two quarts of new Milk, omitting half the whites, and if you will have it a Cream Cuſtard, put no white at all in, add to theſe a pound of fine Sugar, and two ounces of Roſe water, mix them very well, and ſtrain out the liquideſt part very hard; and ſo fill up you Coffins of Paſt: Or, if
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:36870:62"/>you pleaſe you may put it into Pans: if you make a Cream Cuſtard, you may put into it, Nutmeg, and Cloves finely beaten, and ſifted through a Lawn Sieve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Pear Pye.</head>
                  <p>Take hard Winter Pears or Warden, put them into an Earthen Pan, with a little water and ſet them in an Oven, covered with a dough lid or brown Paper wetted, till ſoaked, then skin them, cut them in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and take out Coars, lay in your Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin ſome fine Sugar, and place them in halves, or quarters, neatly upon them, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter betwen each laying, fine beaten Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Cinamon, and ſcrapting of Lemon or Citron peel, then cover them over with Sugar, having put the liquor, that Iſſued in Baking, to them, and ſet the Pye in a pritty quick Oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Pigeon Pye.</head>
                  <p>Draw your Pigeon, dry them well, ſeaſon them with Pepper and Salt, and put ſome fine Pepper, in rowlers of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, into their Bellys, mixed with a little fine ſhred Parſley and Penny-royal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them make laying of Butter, and cloſe them up with the lid, putting But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:36870:62"/>melted and beaten well, when they come out of the Oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Pork Pye.</head>
                  <p>Skin the Pork, and cut it in thin ſlices ſeaſon it with Ginger, Pepper and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, ſprinkle it with Salt and fair Water well Boyled and ſcum'd, lay it in with Butter and the yolks of Eggs well beaten up, and ſome fine grated Manchet, then put in a little Claret, and let it ſoak very well; and it will Eat Exceeding Rare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Quince Pye: Or Tart.</head>
                  <p>Boyl your Quince in Water, Sweetned with Sugar, till they be ſoft, then skin them and take out the Coars, after that Boyl the Water with a little more Sugar, Clove, Cinamon, and Lemon peel, till it becomes of a thickneſs of Syrup, when cold, lay your Quinces in in halves, or quarters, ſcattering Sugar between each laying, put in a pint of the Syrup or more, according to the Biggneſs of your Pye or Tart, make the Coffin round with cloſe or cut covers, and Bake it prety well; and thus you may do with Pippins and Pear-mains, or any Winter Fruit, as alſo with Green Codlings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:36870:63"/>
                  <head>An Oyſter Pye.</head>
                  <p>Take large ſtewing Oyſters, parboyl them, putting into water, a little Pepper, Salt, and Ginger, and being taken out ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them lightly with the ſame, and little grated Nutmeg, rowl them up in little balls of Butter, and beaten Thime, laying them in your Coffin, and pour in a little Claret, and Gravy of Mutton or Beef, cloſe up the lid, and bake them in a gentle Oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Rice Tart.</head>
                  <p>Dreſs the Rice very clean, boyl it with new Milk till it ſwell very much, then ſea-it with grated Nutmeg, beaten Ginger, and Cinamon, beat up ſix yolks of Eggs, with a little Salt, Sugar, and the juice of two Oranges, cloſe up theſe Materials, and when it is to be ſerved up, ſcrape a little fine Sugar over the lid of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Tongue Pye.</head>
                  <p>Take a large Neats-Tongue, or other Tongues, well boyled and blanched, cut it in thin ſlices, lay layings of that, and thin ſlices of ſat Bacon, but of a leſſer quantity, ſeaſon them with Nutmeg, Pepper, pour upon them ſome diſſolved Anchovy, beat up the yolks of five or ſix Eggs Claret and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:36870:63"/>Butter, boyl them up to a thickneſs, and pour them in when the Pye is baked: So a <hi>Hare Pye,</hi> or lean <hi>Veniſon</hi> may be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Veniſon Paſty.</head>
                  <p>Bone your Veniſon, beat it thin, ſeaſon it with Pepper, Nutmeg and Salt, lay it with layings of Butter, or Marrow, on your paſt you deſign for the bottom, cloſe up the lid, and bake it in a ſoaking Oven four hours, then boyl the bones in a pot, with Clarres, Nutmeg, and a little Pepper, and when it is hot ſtrain it, and pour it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Paſty, and cut it up hot or cold, at diſcreſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Lumber Pye.</head>
                  <p>Take the Umbles of Deer, cut them in thin ſlices, ſeaſon them with Salt, Pepper, Nutmeg, and Ginger, lay layings of them with interlarded Bacon, ſliced Dates; Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, and Currant; and when it is going into the Oven, pour into it, Gravy, Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, and Butter beaten up together prity warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Minced Pye.</head>
                  <p>Take a Calves <hi>Chaldron,</hi> Beef, or Neats Tongue, parboyl them, blanch the latter, and mince either of them ſmall, put to a pound half a pound of Currans, and a
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:36870:64"/>quarter of a pound of Beef Suet, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſome thin ſlices of Canded Orange peel, or Lemon peel, a little fine grated Bread, and a gill of Canary, ſprinkle them with Sugar, beaten Mace, Nutmeg and Cinamon: So cloſe up the whole and bake it in a gentle Oven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Putt-Paſt to make.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound and a half of the beſt But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſix Eggs, well beaten up, when they are mixed with new Milk into a paſt, beat them together with a Rowling pin, adding more Flower, Butter and Eggs, as you beat them; and when the paſt is ſoft, and Plyable, Rowl it very thin, for Tiffany Tarts, Cheeſecakes, or the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>A Hern Pye.</head>
                  <p>Break the Breaſt-bone of the Hern, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyl it in water and ſalt, ſhred ſweet herbs with Onyons, and make them up into little Balls, with Butter, put them into the belly, and ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt and Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Cheeſecakes.</head>
                  <p>Take a Gallon f new Milk, put to it a quarter of a Pint of Runnet, and if the Milk be a little warmed, it will preſently curdle, then preſs it in a linen cloth,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:36870:64"/>till all the Whey be run out, beat up the Curd with beaten Cinamon, grated Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, the yolks of half a Dozen of Eggs, finely beaten, and gill of Canary, add a quarter of a pound of pick'd and waſhed Currans, and three ounces of Sugar a pound of Curd, and a gill of Canary to the whole, mix them well, put them in Puff-paſt, and faſhion them as you pleaſe; ſprinkle a few Currans on the top, and waſh them over with a feather dipp'd in Yolks of Eggs, beaten up with Canary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Gooſeberry Tart.</head>
                  <p>Pick your Gooſeberrys clean, lay them in the Sun to dry a little, lay them into the Paſt, with layings of Sugar, ſprinkle them with Roſe-water, and ſccater a few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed Comfits amongſt them, bake them in a gentle Oven. Thus you may uſe Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tarts, Curran Tarts, Apricocks, Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Tarts, and Tarts of all ſoft Plumbs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="pastry_recipe">
                  <head>Chicken Pye.</head>
                  <p>Draw your Chickens, break the breaſts or flat them, ſeaſon them with Pepper and Salt, ſhred Parſley very ſmall, rowl it up with Butter, and put it into them bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys, lay a laying of Butter betwen them,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:36870:65"/>cloſe up the Pye, and bake it, pouring in a ſupply of melted Butter when it is baked; and thus you may order a Hen-Pye, a Gooſe Pye, a Turkey Pye, a Rabbit Pye, only avoiding the parſlley; and with parſley a Lark Pye, or a Pye of any ſmall Birds.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Currous Art of Candying, Preſerving. Conſerving, Drying, and Confectioning, of Flowers, Fruits, Roots, Stalks, Peels, Seeds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Making of Paſts, Marmalades, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Flowers to Candy.</head>
                  <p>TAke Cowſlips, Violets, Clovegilly-flowers, or any other that are of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant taſt and ſmell, pick them clean from the Stalks, and clip off that end that groes in the Husk, dry them moderatly in the Sun, by ſpreading them on a clean linen cloth, then put two pound or more of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, according to the quantity of your flowers, to as much Roſe-water, as will
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:36870:65"/>juſt diſſolve it, boyl it up into a Syrup, and then put in your Flowers, after that, boyl it up over quicker fire, till it Candys, ſo take off, ſtir them with a ſpoon and bruiſe the Sugar from them, and they will be Candy'd without any clog of Sugar upon them, put them up in papered boxes, and ſet them in a warm place, and they will keep good and dry all the Year; and thus you may order any Flowers, or Bloſoms,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Rucket, Orange, or Lemon-peel, Citrons, Erigngo-roots, or Lettice-ſtalks to Candy <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Cleanſe either of theſe from ſuperfluity, and dry out part of the moiſture, then boyl them tender in fair water, Shifting the water once or twice, then waſh them in cool water, and dry them with a cloth, cutting them into what convenient pieces you think fit, take twice ſo much as they weigh in Sugar, refine your Sugar, and boyl them in one half, till they be tender and clear, make your Syrup firſt, with half Roſe-water, and the other half fair-water, and when they are clear, let a Syrup be made of the other half of your Sugar, and boyl them up, ſhake them afterwards till they be cold, and ſo place them on Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:36870:66"/>in a warm place, till they be dry and keep them as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Barberrys, Grapes, or Gooſeberrys to Candy.</head>
                  <p>Firſt preſerve them by boyling them up in a thin Syrup of Sugar and Water, after they have been boyled a little tender in water only, and having waſhed off the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup in a little warm water, ſtrew them over with ſearſed Sugar, and ſet them in a warm Oven or Stove three or four times, not letting them cool till they be dry, and they will ſparkle very curiouſly, and keep long.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Rock Candy very Clear.</head>
                  <p>Take Spices or Flowers, or any dry Suckets, or Fruits, after they are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and dryed, lay them upon a Wier Grate, over an Earthen pan, take refined Sugar, and as much Water as will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it, <hi>viz.</hi> near half a pint to every pound, then beat into it the white of an Egg, when it is hot, and ſet it on the fire again; and when it boyls up, drop a little cold Water into it ſet it off the fire again, and ſcum it, ſo boyl it to a candy height, till it will draw like a hair be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your fingers, then pour it very hot into an Earthen pan among your Fruits,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:36870:66"/>ſet it in a warm place, and cover it cloſe with a Blancket, the next day pour out all the Syrup that will run from it, and ſet your pot in a warm place again, to let them dry, prick up your Wires, take off all the fruit, and lay them in Papers, and when they are thorow dry, they will be a curious Rock-candy then box them up and keep them for uſe; and by theſe rules you may candy any other things that are proper ſo to be ordered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Cherries to Preſerve.</head>
                  <p>Gather your Cherries, when Ripe, in a fair day that the moiſture may be off them, cut off the tops of the ſtolks, and lay them in a pan upon a thin bed of Sugar, put a pound of beaten Loaf Sugar to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very pound of Cherries, and as you boyl them up, ſprinkle ſome Sugar on them, and ſcum them when they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſeeth over, let it be a over quick fire, and they will not break, if you do not too many of them together; two pound is ſufficient at a time, then put them into a broad diſh a cooling, till the next day, and if there come any water from them, ſeeth them a little more; and ſo put them up in the Syrup of Sugar for your uſe;
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:36870:67"/>and in this manner you may preſerve all ſort of Plumbs, Apricocks, Peaches, or Nectrals.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Preſerve Quinces</head>
                  <p>Wipe them clean, cut them in four quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and take out the coar, place the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters regularly in an Earthen pot, and put as much Conduit-water or Spring-water, as will cover them, then ſet them one a gentle fire, and let them ſeeth till they be ſoft, but not break, ſo lay them in a diſh, and when they are cold take off the skin, let the water boyl after to the Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a third part, then put a pint of it to a pound of fine beaten Sugar, and when the Sugar is diſſolved, then ſeeth it till it boyl up into a Syurup, ſcum it and put in the Quinces, and let them ſeeth ſoftly a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, and you perceive them red, then turn them that they may be all of one colour, and ſo keep them in the Syrup cloſe Stoped for your uſe; and in this manner you may preſerve Pippins, and all other winter Fruits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Marmalade of Quinces.</head>
                  <p>Take three Gallons of Spring, or Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-water, pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſixteen pound of Quinces, quarter them and cut out the Coars, put
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:36870:67"/>to theſe eight pound of fine Sugar, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et them all boyl ſoftly, till half the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er be conſumed; and if you would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our Marmalade white, cover them very cloſe during the boyling, and being of a good colour, break them with your ſpoon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d boyl them up to the thickneſs of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alade, then if you pleaſe to have it ſcent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you may diſſolve into it a little Musk, Ambergreeſe, or Roſe-water, and when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> begins to cleave to the ſpoon take it from the Fire, fill it into boxes or pots, ſmooth it and cover it over with a little fine Sugar; and thus you may make Marmalade of Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, Apricocks, Plumbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Marmalade of Oranges, Lemon, or Citrons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take the Peels of either, clean ſcraped within, and thinly pared without, boyl them tender, ſhifting in three waters, to take away the bitterneſs till they have loſt a great part of their taſte, then maſh them in a Mortar, with a wooden peſtle, boyl up Syrup with half a point of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a pound of Sugar and when it is of a good thickneſs, put in the Orange pulp, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and boyl it up, ſcumming off the Froth, to the thickneſs of Marmalade,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:36870:68"/>and ſcent it with Roſe-water, or Orange water, and put it up in Boxes, or lay it on a Plate and dry it into Paſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Paſt of Oranges, and Lemons. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Boyl the Peel tender, as the former, putting into the firſt water a handful of Bay-ſalt, and ſhift them often till the biting taſt is gone, beat them to Maſh, and ſtrain the Pulp through a Cuſhion of Canvas, and mingle ſomething more then the weight in Sugar, then boyl it up till you can ſpread it in cakes, and Faſhioning it as you pleaſe, pritty thin, dry it in places, and keep it in a warm place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Paſt of Plumbs.</head>
                  <p>Take tender Plumbs, as many as you pleaſe, put them in an Earthen pot, and put that pot into a pot of boyling Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but let no water come to the Plumbs, and when they begin to diſſolve, preſs out the thinner part from them through a fine cloth, then ſtrain the Pulp through a canvas, take as much Sugar as it weighs and put to it as much Water as will melt it, ſo boyl it to a Candy height, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving boyled the Pulp very well, put that and the Sugar hot together, ſo boyl them with ſturring, and lay them out to dry on plates, in what form you pleaſe.
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:36870:68"/>And thus you make Paſt, of Cherrys, Rasbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys, Strawberrys, Currans; and indeed, of moſt pleaſant Pruit, and Flowers, and by making them ſomewhat thinner, they will be a fine Marmalode: Or thus, by only putting them in the Syrup without Maſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they may be preſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Conſerve any hard Fruits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>When you have brought them to a paſt by the beforementioned ruley, read to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion upon your plate, inſtead of drying it, put it up in a well glazed pot, ſtrew it over with a little fine Sugar, and Roſe-water; and this way will take, eſpecially with all hard Fruits, as Pippins, Oranges, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Conſerve of Tender Fruits</head>
                  <p>Diſſolve theſe eſpecially Plumbs Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as you did for the paſt, ſtrain the Liquor and Pulp together, putting to every pint three quarters of a pound of Sugar, ſo boyl it up till it becomes indifferent thick, then lay it on a cold diſh till it will ſpread no broader, and ſo put it up in your pots, ſtrew it over with Sugar, and tye it over with a paper, and over that a Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Preſerve Fruits Green.</head>
                  <p>Take Pippins, Apricocks, Peaches, Pear-plumbs,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:36870:69"/>or as you pleaſe, when, gree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcald, them till they will peel pritty eaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then being peeled, boyl them very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, take their weight of Sugar, and diſolv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it in as much water as will cover them then boyl them ſomething leiſurely, take them up and boyl the Syrup until it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſomewhat thick, that it will button upon the Diſh-ſide; and when they are coo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> put them up together, keeping them clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſtopped.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To preſerve Ripe Plumbs, or other Fruit.</head>
                  <p>Take their weight in Sugar and put b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a little water, for theſe will yield liquo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of themſelves, boyl them pritty quick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or the Syrup will turn red; and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you ſee they are enough, put them up i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pots, and keep them ſtopped; and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you may preſerve any Ripe Fruit that requires it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Dry Pippins, an Amber Clearneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Yellow Pippins, pare them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and cut them in halves, taking out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coar, lay them in a baſon of water, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> take their weight in Sugar, Clarifie it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> boyl it almoſt to a Candy height, then dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Pippins with a clean linnen cloth, pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:36870:69"/>them into the Hot Sugar, permitting them to boyl as faſt as they can, when they raiſe take them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff the fire and ſcum them, turn them and ſet them on again; and when the Sugar i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Candy height, lay the Pippi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s in a broad Diſh, and place them in a warm Oven, or Stove, turn them often, and at three days end they will be Dry and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Princes Bisket.</head>
                  <p>Take a pound of Sugar, as much fine Flower, eight yolks of Eggs and 6 whites, beat the Eggs, and make theſe two a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with Milk, mix with it ſome Carra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-Comfits, put it into Tin Coffins, and run it over with a little Canary, and the yolk of an Egg, beaten together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make March-pane of Raſhers of Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</head>
                  <p>Take ſome of the <hi>March-pane,</hi> and knead it in Saunders till it be red, then rowl a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad three rows, of the red and four of the white, lay together a white and a red rowl, until all are layed, then cut them overthwart in thin ſlices, and dry them; and they will deceive the curious, who cannot but take them for Bacon, unleſs you taſt or ſmell them, the Compoſition
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:36870:70"/>is as the other <hi>Macrhpane,</hi> only in this th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> colour added.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Comfits to make of any ſmall Seed, as Carraway, Annis, Coriander, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Boyl your Sugar to a Gandy height, which is, when it will draw at the end of a ſpoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> like a Hair, then your Seeds being dryed fling them in, and ſtir them up and down till they have taken up the Sugar, and are run into ſmall diviſions, then put them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two covers and ſhake them together to looſen them form each other, run them through a Sieve, and dry them in an Oven or Stove, Thus Almonds, or greater Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are Sugred over, and afterwards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed, by putting a grain of Musk into the Box wherein you place them, keeping them cloſe for three or four days. If you would have your Almonds very ſmooth in the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, only dip them into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Rowl-Wafers to make.</head>
                  <p>Take a quarter of a peck of the fineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Flower, make it with whites of Eggs and a little Iſinglaſs diſſolved in water into a kind of a Puff-paſt, by extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary beating; and if you would have them ſweet, or Scented, you may add Sugar or Scents, at your diſcretion; rowl them
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:36870:70"/>out as thin as may on your rowling board, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd having made what impreſſions you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſe on them, rowl them up in hollow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owlers, like rowls of Paper, dry them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a warm Oven; for their thinneſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ires not baking in a hot one; and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e them, either to eat, or rather to Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n, or ſet out Banquets of Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eats.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Cake-Royal, with Comfits.</head>
                  <p>Take a peck of fine Flowers, the yolks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> two dozen of Eggs, four pound of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urrans, two pound of Comfits, 1 pound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Orange peel, Lemon peel, Citron, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngo, and Orris, cut it in little long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts, with two pound of ſweet Butter, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> little Cinamon, and Mace, finely beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and ſifted, make it about two inches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d a half thick, place it in a Tin Hoop, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for want of that in a Wooden one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke it in a brisk Oven, till it be half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nough, then draw it forth, and Ice it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver with Canary, Roſe-water, the white <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> an Egg and Sugar, beaten up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So ſet it in till the Icing becomes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> white as Snow, and it ceaſes to ſwell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y longer.</p>
                  <p>Your ſmall Toys, made of Sugar in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ape of Birds, Beaſts, Flowers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:36870:71"/>made of melted Sugar, in Roſe-water, Caſt in moulds, and Guilded or Painted afterward at Diſcretion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To Blanch Almonds.</head>
                  <p>Or take off their Husks in order to uſe them, is no more than Putting them into warm water till they ſwell, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by ſifting or rubbing them with a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas, the husks will ſeparate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Syrup of Roſes.</head>
                  <p>Gather Damask Roſes, the Dew being on them, about ſix pound, or according to the proportion of the quantity of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup you intend to make, cut away the Whites, at the bottom, then boyl them in as much ſpring-water, as will cover them an Inch in a Glazed Earthen Veſſel do this over a gentle Fire for three o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> four hours, then take out the Roſes, and wring them into the water as hard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may be with a Cloth, put in freſh Roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> till it be very ſtrong of the ſcent, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> turn rediſh, then to ſix pound of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> water, put four pound of Sugar, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> boyl it up to a Syrup. This is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant purging Syrup, not any ways offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſive to the Stomach, and is therefore u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually given to Children on that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and this way, or by infuſion in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:36870:71"/>water, Syrup of Violets, Couſlips, Clove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilly-flowers, and other ſimple Syrups, of Flowers, Herbs, Fruits, and Roots, are made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Cordial Syrup of Poppeys.</head>
                  <p>Take the heads of white poppeys, not throughly blown, eight ounces, the heads of black ones, ſix ounces, Aqua Coeleſtis, two quarts, ſimper them over a gentle fire, to the conſumption of a third part, then add 3 pound of Sugar to the liquor, the poppeys being ſqueezed out, ſome blades of Mace, and bits of Cinamon boyled in other water, to the quantity of half a pint, poured into this, then boyl it up to the thickneſs of a Syrup: It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good againſt Cattars, and Coughs, and in Feavers, mittigating the heat and pain; it helpeth Frenzies, and Watchings, and procureth Sleep. And thus with Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtis, Brandy, or Aqua-vitae, you may make any Cordial Syrups.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Syrup for any Cold, Cough, or Cattar.</head>
                  <p>Take one ounce of Cetrack, Coltsfoot, the herb ſo called, and Maiden-hair, each one ounce, boyl them in three quarts of water, till it waſtes to three pints, with one pound of Elecampain roots ſliced, then ſtrain out the liquid part, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="172" facs="tcp:36870:72"/>it up with a pound and a half of Sugar, to a Syrup, and take a dram of it in any covenient warm liquor, Night and Morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Honey of Raiſins to make.</head>
                  <p>Take Raiſins of the Sun two pound, ſtone them and infuſe them 24 hours in ſix pound of warm water, then boyl it to the conſumption of half, ſo ſtrain and preſs it out, then adding two pound of diſpumated Hony, boyl it to the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Hony. And thus you may make Hony of Violets, Roſes, or other Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſweet Fruits, or Herbs, proper to any uſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Marchpanes.</head>
                  <p>Blanch your Almonds ſwell'd in cold water, beat them in a ſtone Mortar, and drop in your beating, ſome Roſewater into them, keep them from Oyling, and ſtrew now and then a handful of fine ſifted Sugar, and when by working you have brought it unto a Paſt, rowl it thin, and make it into its form; Ice it over with Roſe-water, Sugar, and the white of an Egg beaten together, put it into a moderate hot Oven, and when the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing begins to riſe, take it out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:36870:72"/>
                  <head>To make Makroons.</head>
                  <p>Take to a pound of Blanched Almonds, half a pound of fine Sugar, beat them in a Wooden or Stone Mortar, with whites of Eggs, and a little Roſe-water, till they come to be as thick as Batter for Fritters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>en lay wafers on your Tin Plates, put on this Batter in little ſpoonfuls, ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it over with a little fine Sugar and Roſe-Water; and ſo Bake them in a Gentle Oven, about a Quarter of an Hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make French Bisket.</head>
                  <p>Take half a peck of Flower, four Eggs, and half a pint of Ale Yeaſt, an ounce and a half of Anniſeeds, make them up into a Paſt, with a little Cream, and cold water, faſhion it like a long Brick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and when it is a day or two old cut it out into thin ſlices, like Toaſts, being ſtrewed over with beaten Loaf-Sugar, ſet them in a warm Oven or Stove, till they are dryed; and ſo put them in boxes for uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Naples Bisket</head>
                  <p>Take Almonds beaten very fine, one pound, fine Flower a pound and a half, Sugar one pound, whites of Eggs half a Dozen, make them into Batter with fair
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:36870:73"/>water, and put the Batter into your Tin Coffins, ſo bake them, glazing them with the white of an Egg, and Roſe-water</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Artificial Embelliſhments: Or, the Art of Beautifying the Hands, Face, or any other part of the Body; Reſtoring a good Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, taking away Freckles, Spots, or any Deformities in the Skin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Making Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, Eſſences, Sweet-bags, Sweet-balls, Pomatums, Waſhes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To Beautifie the Hands and Face.</head>
                  <p>TAke two handfuls of Roſemary Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, one handful of the tops of Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitory, and an ounce of Blanched Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, groſly bruiſed, boyl theſe in a quart of ſpring-water, and a pint of White-wine, till a fifth part be conſumed, then ſtrain out the reſt, let it ſettle twenty-four hours in a Glaſs, then pour it off from the ſetlings, and uſe it as an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Beautifier, and great Reſtorer of a good complexion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:36870:73"/>
                  <head>To make the Skin ſoft, and White.</head>
                  <p>Take Neats-foot Oyl, one ounce, Oyl, or the Fat that ſwims upon the boyling of Sheeps Trotters, a like quantity, mix theſe in half a pint of Roſe-water, over a gentle fire, and ſupple the parts with it very warm, chafing or rubbing it in, a few times doing it will anſwer your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take away Morphew, Scurff, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deformities of the Skin.</head>
                  <p>Take Comphire, two drams, two Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>viz.</hi> the juice of them, Loaf-Sugar an ounce, mix theſe in half a pint of fair water, put it into a Glaſs, and ſhake it often, ſuffering it to ſtand eight or ten days in the Sun, or ſome warm place, then add a ſcruple of white ſublimated Mercury, ſhake it about and ſtrain it, and when you would uſe it, put it ſoftly to your Face, with a linnen rag or cloth, or upon any other place, and it will take off the Deformity, and under that, there will as it were, a new Skin appear, very Freſh and Lively.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take away Redneſs, or Pimples from the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take Camphire a dram, Copperas half an ounce, Wine Vinegar half a pint, add
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:36870:74"/>to theſe the Rhind of Citron thinly pared, one ounce, boyl them to the conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a third part, then ſtrain and preſs out the liquid part, and waſh the Face with it, anointing it afterward with Oyl of Roſes, and Tuttia, mingled together, and let it lye on all night, and in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time the Redneſs, or Pimples will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, and the Skin recover its ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and natural Complection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take away Freckles.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gaul of a young Cock, the Wool of a Hares foot, burnt to powder, by wrapping it up hard in a Brown pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per wetted, as in Burning Silver Lace, that it may not Burn to Aſhes, but Moulder, and ſo be reducible into Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, add to theſe an ounce of Rye-Meal, beat them together with the Pulp of a Lemon, and Wine Vinegar, till they may be ſpread Playſter-wiſe, ſpread this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on ſoft Leather, and lay it on the Freckley places; and in twice or thrice applying, you will ſee a ſtrange Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To cauſe a curious White, Shining Complection.</head>
                  <p>Take Peach Bloſſoms, two handfuls, the Sap that drops from a cut Vine, 4
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:36870:74"/>ounce, the ſeed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Mellions groſly bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, one ounce Gum Tragacanth, beaten finely into Powder, half an ounce, put to theſe, when well beaten, or bruiſed, two quarts of Clarified Whey, let them infuſe twenty-four hours in a warm place, then preſs out the Liquid part as hard as may be by preſſing, and uſe it as you ſee occaſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To make the Hands or Face Plump.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Marrow of the Bones of Hogs Feet two ounces, Oyl of Almonds, and Oyl of Roſes, each half an ounce, Flower of Almonds finely ſifted, half an ounce, make theſe up into an Unguent, and chafe it in often, and it will Supple and Plump the Skin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to a curious Softneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>A curious Perfume againſt ill Scents.</head>
                  <p>Take Frankincenſe, a quarter of an ounce, in Powder, Myrrh, the like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, Lavender flowers, and Roſemary leave, beaten into pwder, mix them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put them into an Incenſe pot, or ſprinkle them on a Chafing-Diſh of Coals.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>A Sweet-Bag to Scent Cloaths &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Take tops of Hyſop, Winter Savou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Roſemary, Lavender, and the chip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:36870:75"/>of Caſſa Ligna, Cedar, and Saſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frax, few them up in thin bags, and lay them among your Garments, and they will not only give them a curious Scent, but preſerve them from Worms, Moths, or any other Inſects.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>Sweet Balls to cary in ones Hand, for the Prevention of ill Airs or Scents.</head>
                  <p>Take Paſt e of Almonds four ounces, mingle with it a little Bean-Flower, then knead it, being made wet with Orange, or Jeſſime water, and drop two or three drops of the Oyl of Cloves, Nutmeg, Cina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or any other Scents as you will pleaſe to have it Scented with, and make them up into Balls, or hollow Boxes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>Sweet Powder.</head>
                  <p>Take Rice grounds, beat them, dry them, and ſift them often, till they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very fine, then dry them again, ſcent a pound of this with two grains of Musk, a dram of Roſe ſcent, or other ſcents proper, that is pleaſing to you. This may be done for want of Rice grounds, with White Starch, finely ſif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>A Perfume to Drive away Vermin,</head>
                  <p>Take Storax a quarter of an ounce, Aſſafoetida, as much, the Bark of Elder-root,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:36870:75"/>and a few tops of Southern-wood, dry the latter, and beat them ſeverally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to powder, then mix them and ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle them on a hot Fire-Shovel, or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing-diſh of Coals, keeping the place, Cloſe, and either, Mice, Rats, Bugs, Flyes, Moths, or Worms, that are within the ſcent of it, will avoid the place; and if it be often continued, never return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>A Bath, to ſoften, Cleanſe, and Refreſh the Body.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of White-Lillies, and Marſh-mallows of each two pound, Groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, Pelletory of the Wall, and Violets, each half an handful, Linſeed, Fenugreek, and Coriander-ſeeds, each four ounces, Flowers of Camomile, Mellilot, and tops of Fennel, each half a handful, boyl a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hours in a ſufficient quantity of water, then add Oyl of Lillies, and Lindſeed, each a pound, and either bathe your ſelf in it in a Bathing-tub, warm, or apply it with Linnen-cloths.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>Water of Talc, a great Beautifier.</head>
                  <p>Take the beſt Talc, ſlit it in thin peices, hang it up in a thin Linnen Bag in a very damp place, with a Receiver under it to receive the droppings, when
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:36870:76"/>if ſweats, or diſſolves, then diſtil it, and it produces a curious Shining Beatifying Water, to ſet a Lovely Whiteneſs on the Skin, and keep back the ſigns of Age.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take Spots, or Stains, out of Silks or Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take a Trotter-bone, burn in and beat it to powder, mix it with Fullers earth, and a little Caſteel Soap, wet it in fair water, rub it on the place, and then dry it in the Sun, or by a gentle fire, then rub it over hard with a wet Brtſh, and when it is dry again, the Spot or Stain will diſappear.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take out Pitch, Wax, Poſin or Tar.</head>
                  <p>If any of theſe happen on a Garment either Silk, Linnen, or Woollen, pour a a little Oyl of Turpentine on the place, and let it ſoak in about half an hour, then rub it out, but not too hard; and you will find the Turpentine has Soaked out the Gluttonous quality, ſo tht it will crumble out, like ſmall bits of dry Dirt, or Clay.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take Spots, or Stains out of Linnen.</head>
                  <p>Take the juice of a Lemon, and red Onyon mixed together, put into it a-little
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:36870:76"/>Gum Sandrack, and Crumbs of Stale White-bread, heat theſe gently over a Fire, and then dip the part that is ſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed often in it, let it then dry, and have in readineſs a hot Lather of Soap and Water, to waſh it immediately; and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo in two or three Waſhings, it will quite diſappear.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To Source, or Clean, Gold and Silver Lace.</head>
                  <p>Lay it on a Carpet very even, then with a ſoft Bruſh run it over with fine Bran, three or four times, to take off the Dirt, then to brighten it, take burnt Alom, beaten to fine Powder, and ſifted, rub this powder on gently with a Bruſh, in all places where the Tarniſh is, and it will anſwer your expectation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>Faided Linnen to recover.</head>
                  <p>If Linnen by being too much expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the Weather, or received Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by Sea, or Scorched, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Make a Lather of Coſteel Soap, boyl your Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen in it, then immediately throw it into cold water and Fullers-earth pritty hot, and thickly mixed, then waſh it out in the firſt Lather, and wring it light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hang it to dry in the Shade, and it will not only thicken, and whiten, but be freſh and ſtrong.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:36870:77"/>
                  <head>How to make a Starch, that will preſerve Linnen.</head>
                  <p>Take the Bran of the firſt fine Wheat, ſteep it in water two days, then let that water run through 2 or three fine Sieves, ſo put it in an Earthen Diſh, and ſet it in the Sun, or over a gentle fire, till it dry, and become a Starch.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To make your Teeth as White as Ivory.</head>
                  <p>Take Lapis Calaminaris, burnt and beat to fine Powder, alſo Powder of fine Pumice-Stone, put them into a little White-wine, and being Moiſtened, dry them again in an Oven or ſome warm place; and ſo reducing it to powder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, rub your Teeth with it, either with your Finger, or a little Bruſh, and then waſh your mouth with Small-beer, wherein Sage has been boyled; and by this means they will not only become white, but faſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>To take Spots out of the Face, or Hands.</head>
                  <p>Take a Burdock-root, ſcrape it and ſlice it thin, boyl it in Sheeps Milk, and bruiſe into it two or three Galls of the French Oak, and with the Liquid part wet
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:36870:77"/>the Spots often, and they will fade by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and at laſt diſappear.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="beauty_tip">
                  <head>A Pomatum for the Hands, to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Chopping, or Roughneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take Deer-ſuet half an ounce, white Bees-wax a quarter of an ounce, Sperma Ceti an Ounce, Oyl of Amber 2 drams, Oyl of Almonds an ounce, incorporate theſe over a gentle Fire, and make them into a convenient thickneſs, and Anoint the Hands or Face with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Notwithſtanding I have given you Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the making ſeveral ſorts of Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticks, there is one already prepared, called.</hi> The VENETIAN WASH, <hi>&amp;c, And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s ſold for Twelve-pence the Bottle, by</hi> S. Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>in</hi> George-yard <hi>in</hi> Lombard-ſtreet, <hi>Mr.</hi> Levingſton<hi>'s</hi> Fruit-ſhop, <hi>the South Enterance of the</hi> Royal-Exchange. <hi>Which I know to be Extraordinary Good, for Clearing and ſmoothing the skin; and Rendring the Face very Beautiful and Lovely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At the ſame Places are ſold, a Moſt Admirable Powder called,</hi> A Dentifrice for Whitening the Teeth; <hi>which will make Teeth though as Black as Ebony, as White as Ivory.</hi> Price Six Pence the <hi>Box.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:36870:78"/>
                  <p>Thus have I made Good my <hi>Promiſe</hi> to you in laying before you ſuch things as I thought would prove acceptable to you: So not Doubting you will Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, as they were intended for your Good; and ſo Profit by them, that you may have the Benefits I Wiſh you, grown Weary with Writing I put and End to this Book.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36870:79" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36870:79"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36870:80" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36870:80"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
